<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Relation of sixtene martyrs glorified in England in twelve moneths] [with a declaration, that English catholiques suffer for the catholique religion, and that the seminarie priests agree with the Jesuites / by Thomas Worthington]</title>
            <author>Worthington, Thomas, 1549-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26000.9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S5341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">39960833</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 39960833</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150527</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73454)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150527)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1952:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Relation of sixtene martyrs glorified in England in twelve moneths] [with a declaration, that English catholiques suffer for the catholique religion, and that the seminarie priests agree with the Jesuites / by Thomas Worthington]</title>
                  <author>Worthington, Thomas, 1549-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[98] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the widow of James Boscard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at Doway :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page lacking. Title, author, and imprint information from typed surrogate.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸, added leaf: An Advertisement to the reader.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, worn, stained, with print show-through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Martyrs --  England.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:2"/>
            <p>Relation of sixtene mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs glorified in England in twelve monethes. With a declaration, That English catholiques suffer for the catholique religion, and That the Seminarie priests agree with the Jesuites.</p>
            <p>By Thomas WORTHINGTON</p>
            <p>Printed at Doway, by the widow of James Bos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card.</p>
            <p>1601.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE MANER OF PROCEDING, AGAINST M. IOHN RIGBIE, a Catholique Gentleman put to death in London, this preſent yeare, 1600.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt other common oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents, which miniſter occation of ſpeach and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, in ſundrie partes of the world, it is neither the leaſt, nor of leaſt importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that is dayly reported of manie Catholiques, put to death and otherwiſe afflicted, theſe late yeares in England. Whoſe preſent hard ſtate, and the true cauſe therof, though the beſt and mightieſt Princes and Potentates of the Chriſtian world (as alſo manie others of al eſtates) do wel ſee and knowe, and with compaſſionable chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie do manie wayes, like the good Samaritan, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> releue and aſſiſt them: yet there be two other ſortes of men, the one not ſufficiently wel, the other very il affected, towards theſe diſtreſſed Catholiques. For the former ſeing and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding their calamities, paſſe on their waies, like the Iudaical and carnal Prieſts and Leuits, as if it nothing at al pertained to them, either
<pb facs="tcp:150527:4"/> to take notice, or to haue care and compaſſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of their neighbours miſeries. Of which kind of people, I haue litle more now to ſay, but hartely pray God, to make them more mercifull, that they may find mercie in the time of nede. For that I am here principally to deale with the laſt ſort, who more actually perſecute Catholiques: not only depriving them by violence, of their goods, liberties, and liues: but alſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and slandering them of hainous crimes, wherof they are moſt free and innocent: to make them odious, or their martyrdom leſſe glorious, amongſt the ignorant at home, and ſtrangers abrode: ſaing and auouching with great wordes, othes, and proteſtations, that they die not, nor ſuffer not, for cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but for matter of treaſon againſt their Quene and Soueraigne: though in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences they can not but knowe it to be farre oterwiſe. For why els (beſides other proofes) are they ſo vnwilling to report, and ſo loath to heare, what maner of treaſon this is, but for that, when the ſame is ſincerly declared, it eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and euidently appeareth, to be no other thing, then mere Religion, and neceſſarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Catholique faith? As hath bene very often proued, not only by other irrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable teſtimonies, and manifeſt demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrations, but alſo by their owne tribunals, in publique place of Iuſtice, in the moſt principal cities and townes of the Realme: as at London, Yorke, Lanceſton, Chenceford, Lancaſter, Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:4"/> Durram, Newcaſtle, Carlel, Oxford, Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, Gloceſter, Wrixam, Warwike, Darbie, Stafford, Bewmatis, Nottingam, Canturbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Lincolne, and other places. But for ſomuch as our aduerſaries perſiſt ſtil, in auouching and mantaining their pretended Iuſtice in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, I ſhal for the more honour of God, mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manifeſtation of the truth, and better informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch as be not ſufficiently ſatisfied, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerly relate an other example of trial, made in the cauſe of à Catholique gentleman, put to death in London the 21. day of Iune this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent holie yeare 1600. In which narration, for auoiding of al partialitie, I wil omit other proofes of our Religion, and iuſt commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the partie (which may notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hereafter be more largely published) and ſimply in tvvo woordes, touch thoſe onlie points vvhich concerne the neceſſarie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his perſon, and pertained directly to the cauſe of his death: and then ſet before your eyes the whole proceſſe, as it paſſed before ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie vvitneſſes, in forme and shew of publi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. The diuulging wherof in print, no reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men, and namely the Magiſtrats and others that concurred in this action, can not diſlike, nor poſſibly be offended thervvith, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept their conſciences accuſe them, of ſome vniuſt dealing againſt the perſon, whom they haue ſo publikly apprehended, examined, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, iudged, and bereued of his life. Briefly therefore, his name was M. Iohn Rigbie, one
<pb facs="tcp:150527:5"/> of the younger ſonnes of M. Nicolas Rigbie of Harrock, in the Countie of Lancaſter ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. VVho coming to yeares, ad vſe of reaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent for that purpoſe, ſo ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly learned the principal articles of his faith, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually even to death, he held al the ſame, to be vndoubtedly true, and neceſſarie to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as wel appeareth by that which here fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. He attayned alſo the Latin tongue and further proceded not in learning. The reſt of his youth he ſpent partly in his fathers houſe, partly in ſeruice: where through humaine frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for feare of punishment, and in hope of temporal preferment, ioyned with il example and earneſt perſwaſions, of ſome worldlie freinds, he yelded ſo farre to the Proteſtants Parlament lawes, made for the abolishing of the holie Sacrifice, and other Catholique Rites, and for practice of the new forme of english ſeruice, as to heare ſometimes the ſame ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. But being afterwards very ſorrowful for having ſo conformed him ſelfe, by exteriour act, and perſonal preſence, in the Proteſtants Chruches, (VVhich is there <hi>the note and character</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13</note> 
               <hi>of conformitie</hi> to their religion) and therby alſo depriuing him ſelfe, of the holie Sacraments, and neceſſarie foode of his ſoule <hi>(for none may</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 13</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate of the Altar of Chriſt, that ſerue the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle:</hi> and much leſſe, that ſerue a new Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which was never approued in Gods Church) he reſolued by Gods grace, to leaue againe that courſe of life, and ſo was abſolued
<pb facs="tcp:150527:5"/> from his ſinnes, and reconciled to God, by a Catholique Prieſt. And thence forth liued in great peace of his conſcience, and alacritie of mind, with zeale and feruour of deuotion: by word and example, dravving ſo manie as he could, to the like good eſtate, for their ſoules health. Amongſt others (which I may not here omit, though I promiſed breuitie) by his earneſt prayers, moſt dutiful endeuour, and Godlie perſuaſions, he procured his owne father to be reconciled to God, in his old age. by which worke of ſingular pietie, and by manie others, he dayly prepared the way, to the glorious crowne, that he novv poſſeſſeth. Wherunto likvviſe concurred certaine other occaſions, which it pleaſed God alſo to permit and to vſe, in bringing him to this bleſſed end.</p>
            <p>For being (as is wel knowne) in the ſeruice of Sir Edmund Hudleſton knight, he was ſent by his maiſter, to Sir Richard Martin Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman of London, about certaine buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Where the young man dealnig ſomewhat roundly and ſincerly, as it became a faithful ſeruant in his maiſters affaires, this Sir Richard conceiued offence and diſpleaſure againſt him. Which he ſtil bore in minde (like Herode and <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Herodias, wayting opportunitie to be reuenged of S. Iohn Baptiſt) til a fit time happened for his purpoſe, as ſhortly it fel out by this accident.</p>
            <p>Maiſtris Forteſcue a Catholique widow, and daughter of the ſame Sir Edmund Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſton, was ſommoned to the Seſſions at New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb facs="tcp:150527:6"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: who being ſicke, and not able to appeare, was to ſend one to teſtifie the ſame for her in that Court. VVhervpon this maiſter Iohn Rigbie her fathers man, and hers alſo when she needed his ſeruice, was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (as God would haue it for his more glorie) to do this good office for her that day. And ſo going to the Seſſions houſe, when Maiſtris Forteſcue was called, he appeared and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that she was ſicke, and not able to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners demanded, if he would auerre the ſame by his oth, he ſaid he would ſo do. A booke was by and by offered him. Wheron he was commaunded to lay his hand (as the maner is) and ſo he did: as being readie to confirme by his oth, that which he had in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to anſwer, according to his opinion and knowledge. But the commiſsioners being much diſcontented, to be thus fruſtrat of the gentlewomans appearance, the forſaid Sir Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Martin (perceuing him to be the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had heretofore bene with him, and had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him) ſuddenly and with choler begaine to examine him of his owne faith and religion, before he was otherwiſe apprehended, or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or had anie cogitation of anſwering for him ſelfe. Which nevertheleſſe he did with admirable reſolution and corage, to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his aduerſaries, and great edification of manie, as wel preſent as others that haue ſince heard therof, and doubtles alſo of more yet, vvhich may hearaſter heare of it. Our. B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niour
<pb facs="tcp:150527:6"/> 
               <hi>geving him mouth and wiſdome</hi> (as he <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> promiſeth in ſuch caſe) <hi>which al his aduerſaries were not able to reſiſt and gainſay.</hi> So from this examination he was carried to priſon amongſt theues, and often after examined, and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from priſon to priſon, and at laſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and put to death, al in ſuch ſorte as now you shal here read. And that for the former and greater part, written by him ſelfe word by word as foloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Copie of my examination the</hi> 14. <hi>of Febru.</hi> 1600. <hi>taken before my Lord mayor of London, M. Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Sir Richar Martin, Iuſtice Dale, with others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Comming to the Seſſions to take my oth, vpon occaſion <hi>(to testifie that Maiſtris Forteſcue was ſicke and not able to appeare in that place)</hi> and having the oth tendered, and my hand vpon the booke to ſweare, ſuddenlye ſpoke Sir Richard Martin, and ſaid: VVhat are you that wil ſweare? à papiſt? to whom taking my hand backe, I anſwered, I am à man. but what more, ſaith he? at which his replie (not able to forbeare laughter) I ſaid: Sir what can I be more then à man? he then ſaid: art thou à Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, a Proteſtant, a Puritan or what Religion art thou of? at which I ſomething ſtaying, he ſaid preſently: wilt thou go to Church, or no? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> here vrg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to which I ſaid, No. I thought ſo, ſaid he, he may ſweare what he liſt, and hath his Prieſt at home to abſolue him, I warrant you. Sir, ſaid I, I do not vſe to make falſe othes, and if I did, I <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> know not anie Prieſt to geue me abſolution
<pb facs="tcp:150527:7"/> ſo eaſely. Then ſpoke my Lord Mayor, will you not go to the Church? No my Lord. were <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> you at Church within this moneth? No. were you within this three moneths? No. were you within theſe twelue monethes? No, my Lord. wil you not go, to the Church? No. when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> you the Commumon? Neuer. nor will you not receiue it? No my Lord, for I know that to be no Sacrament, and therefore wil not receiue it. O damnable creature, ſaid they! what Religion art thou of? à poore Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique my Lord. à Catholique ſaid they! ſo are we. what is the Catholique Religion? that <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>olique <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which I beleeue. and what do you beleeue? That which the whole Catholique Church beleueth, what is that? that which I beleeue, my Lord. ſo I would not be brought from that, by no meanes. I wil warrant you, ſaid Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Martin, he beleueth as his Maiſtris be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth. I pray God I beleue no worſe, ſaid I. whoſe man are you? ſaid my Lord Maior. Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris Forteſcues, my Lord. how long haue you ſerued hir? theſe foure or fiue yeares. who preferred you to her? one Claiton à brother in law of myn. is he a Catholique? No, my Lord à Proteſtant. vvere you à Catholique vvhen you came to her? No my Lord, but alvvayes Catholikely brought vp. Hovv chaunced it that you altered your religion? vvhen I came to riper yeares, my Lord, and conſidered myn ovvne eſtate better, I very wel percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that courſe vvherin I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liued, vvas not
<pb facs="tcp:150527:7"/> the courſe vvhere in to be ſaued. vvherup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, I altered my Religion. VVhat, ſaid Iuſtice Dale, vvilt thou take the oth of the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie? Sir ſaid I, novv you ſeeke my blood, I knovv not al that belongs to that oth. there be manie can anſvvere you better then I. I vvil not ſvveare. No, ſaid they al at once, vvhy? VVe haue al taken it, if thou denieſt it, thou art à traitor. To vvhich I anſvvered, I am no Traytor, my Lord, but à true Subiect. That vvhich your lordship and others haue done, is nothing to me, I vvil not ſvveare. And if the Pope should ſend in forces, to inuade this Realme, vvhoſe part vvould you take, the Quenes or the Popes? I anſvveared, the Quenes my Lord. But if he should come to ſettle the Catholique Religion (as you terme it) vvhoſe part vvould you then take? Good my Lord that concerns my life. I vvil not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver it. vvhat, art thou not à Prieſt? ſaid Sir Richard. No, farre vnvvorthie ſo high a cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? Nor a frere? No. Nor taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nie orders, nor profeſſion vpon you? No more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed my ſelf, by Gods grace, to liue and dy in the Catholique Church. VVere you never out of England? No my Lord. looke if he be not bald, ſaid Iuſtice Dale. No I vvarrant you, ſaid I. ſend for à Barber, ſaid my Lord Maior, and cut of his haire preſently. So vve reſted til the Barber came. Then they ſet me on à vvarme ſtone, vvhere the Irons vvere in heating to burne felons vvithal; and the barber
<pb facs="tcp:150527:8"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to play his part. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had ſitten a litle, the ſtone burned th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o my hoſe, and the fyer vnder burned my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. VVhervpon I ſpoke and ſaid, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to hote, my Lord. And preſently they anſv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red al, thou muſt fit hotter yet. Nay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſaid I, put vnder more fyer in Gods name, vvhearat I heard no one vvord. but, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and by, they ſpoke vnto the barber, and bade him cut me cloſe to the head. VVhen to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſvvered, in this quarel, head and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if it pleaſe you, my Lord. VVhen he had donne they bade me pay the barber. I ſaid, No, my lord Maior should: yet stay ſaid I, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>halt not take al theſe paines for nothing. So I tooke forth my purſe, and gaue him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pence. VVhere at there vvas great laughing, and I not the leaſt merrie, I am ſure Then my Lord called me againe. Hovv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vvil you yet go to Church? I anſvvered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my Lord, this hath not anie vvhit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted me. VVhat Countriman are you? A Lancashire man my Lord, VVhat is your name? Rigbie. vvhat more? Iohn Rigbie. vvhere about in Lancashire? about two miles from Latham, at a houſe called Harrock vvas I borne, my Lord. I am more ſorie, ſaid he, for I knovv honeſt gentlemen of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. If there vvere anie honeſtie amongeſt them, ſaid I, I hope in Ieſus he vvil graunt me part by deſcent. Then ſaid Sir Richard Martin, Sirra Sirra, vvhat prayer doe you vſe
<pb facs="tcp:150527:8"/> dayly to ſay, for the Pope? Sir ſaid I, I knovv not vvhat you meane. Yes ſaid he, that you doe, for you ſay this daylie praier: and began to repete certaine vvordes, vvhich vvere neither English, Latin, French, nor Spani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, I am ſure: but he ment (as it ſemed) to haue made Latin of it. I haue forgot it, and ſo did preſently, for except it had bene vvritten it vvas impoſſibile to carrie it a vvaye. Only the three laſt vvords I remember, vvhich vvere, pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſtra Papa. VVherat not able <note place="margin">That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to forbeare laughter, I vſed an oth or tvvo ſaying: by my faith and troth, I neuer heard ſo ſimple a ſentence come forth of anie Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques mouth: and for myn ovvne part, though I vnderſtand Latin, I do not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand vvhat you ſaid. VVherat al the bench laghed vvith me for companie. So my Lord Maior commaunded the keper to take me againe to his cuſtodie. And I ſtood amongſt the fellons til night, and ſo vvent to nevvgate my nevvlodging. vvhere I learned ſome neck tricks, and there reſted.</p>
            <p>The next day at nine of the clocke when my Lord chiefe Iuſtice vvas ſet in his place, I vvas ſent for to the Seſſions houſe. vvhere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently his Lordship asked my name. I anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Iohn Rigbie. VVhat Cuntriman are you? a Lanca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hire man my Lord. Hovv long haue you continevved in theſe partes? ſome foure or fiue yeares, my Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvith vvhom? in ſeruice vvith M. is Forteſcue. vvhoſe daughter
<pb facs="tcp:150527:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his daughte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhere liueth ſhe? vvith her faither. VVho preferred you to her ſeruice? a brother inlavv of myn, one Clayton, my Lord. VVhat reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion vvere you of, vvhen you came to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hart a Catholique my Lord. but you vvent to Church ſaid he. I did my Lord ſometimes, but alvvayes intended by Gods grace to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Catholique. VVho perſvvaded you to that courſe, to alter your Religion. No bodie my Lord, but myn ovvne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. for vvhen I conſidered myn eſtate, I found that I vvas not in the right courſe to be ſaued. and therfore I reſolued by Gods grace to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that Religion vvherby my ſoule might be ſaued. VVil you not go to the Church? No my Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you liued in Sir Edmund his houſe? I my Lord. Doth Sir Edmund go to the Church? I my Lord. And my Ladie alſo? for any thing I knovv, my Lord. For I tooke no great heed of any bodies going, but myn ovvne. Hovv long haue you refuſed to go to the Church? theſe tvvo or three yeares my Lord. You vvent to the Church once, then can you not be, as you ſay, a Catholique, but you muſt be reconciled. Hovv ſay you then vvere you reconciled or no? vvherto not knovving vvhat to anſvvere, I ſtayed a litle. and his lordship againe bad me ſpeake, then I anſvvered: my lord to ſatisfie your lordship in this point, I tooke not vpon me, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my religion vvith out a certaine ground
<pb facs="tcp:150527:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atholique. I vvas in deede reconciled my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd. vvel ſaid: ſaith he, and by vvhom? by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e M. Buckley my lord, vvas he a Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie Prieſt? he vvas a Catholique Prieſt my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord. vvhere vvas it done? in the Clinck. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ovv came you acquainted vvith him? by a Lancashire man, a kinſman of myn. VVhere is he? dead my lord. hovv many times ſince, haue you ſenne him, at your Maiſtris houſe? Never in my life, neither before nor ſince. VVhat others haue you ſeene there? not one my lord? hovv manie more knovv you thath are Prieſts? Not one my Lord. VVhere is that Buckley novv? in heaven I make no doubt. in heaven! hovv knovv you that? he ſuffered Martyrdom for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion. Did you never ſee him before, and could he perſvvade you ſo fully? I my lord. for by Gods grace I doubted not in anie one article of my beliefe. Al vvhich examination they vvrit dovvne and gaue it me to ſet my hand to it firſt, for honor ſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my lord chief Iuſtice or any of the reſt, vvhich I did. and then they ſet their hands to it alſo. Then my lord commaunded the keper to take me, and to put on me an iron chaine. vvhich vvhen it came I vvilled him to put it on, in Gods name, and ſaid alovvd: I vvould not change my chayne, for my Lord Maior his great chayne, and gaue the felovv ſix pence for his paines. By and by my Lord chiefe
<pb facs="tcp:150527:10"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtice ſent me vvord to prouide my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, for I vvas to be arrayned forthvvith. I bad the meſſenger tel his Lordship. I neuer heard ſo good nevves in my life before, and ſo I vvas commannded to the common Gayle. But (expecting everie day to be arreigned) the Tueſday folovving, I vvas removed to the vvhit Lyon in Southvvork. and vvas there quiet til the third of March, not hearing anie more vvhat should be done vvith me.</p>
            <p>On vvenſday, the third of March in the common Seſſions vvith a number of felons I vvas brought to my trial. In the forenon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I vvas called and appeared, but nothing vvas ſaid to me. VVhen the Iuſtice vvent to diner vve alſo vvent home to priſon. and benig at dinner Iuſtice Gaudie ſent his man for me, and I vvent vvillingly vvith my keper. And ſo coming to them at Iuſtice Dale his houſe vvhere the Iudges dined, Iuſtice Gaudie commanded the chamber to be voided, ſaing there vvere matters of importance to be delt in. Some vvent avvay, but the moſt part ſtayed. There he called me vnto him, and asked my name, vvhich I told him. vvere not you committed by my Lord chiefe Iuſtice, and examined by him at Newgaae? I my Lord, I vvas ſo. You knovv your ovvne hand if you ſee it? I my Lord. ſo he shevved me my hand, and I ſaid: This is my hand. I pray you geue me leaue to ſpeake for my ſelfe. You shal, ſaid he. I vvel perceiue you haue
<pb facs="tcp:150527:10"/> thougt better of the matter ſince, or are growne far more skilfull. This manner of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering for your ſelf before, would haue ſerued your turne better: but now it wil not. I ſent for you to this end. I am told by one of my Lord of Canturburie his gentleman, that you thought you had anſwered before igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, and are now ſorie for that you haue done, and willing to become a good Subiect, and go to Church. If you wil ſo do, her Maieſtie is merciful, and her Lawes wil take pitie vpon you. How ſay you, wil you go to Church now? No my Lord. Good my Lord, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> who ſoeuer informed your Lordship, that euer I did yet yeld, in anie point of my profeſſion, or former anſwer, was not my freinde, nor euer had my conſent therto. I aſſure you, my Lord, I am a true Subiect, and obedient to her Maieſtie and her Lawes, in anie thing which may not hurt my conſcience. But to ſay that I wil go to Church, I neuer did, nor neuer wil. Yea rather, my Lord, then your Lordship should haue anie light ſuſpicion of me, of ſuch a conſent, take my firſt anſwere, as it is, there is my hand, here is my whole bodie, moſt readie I am, and willing to ſeale it with my bloode and I humbly thanck your Lordship, for calling me to anſwere this point my ſelf. VVhy then, ſaid both the iudges, wil you not go to Church? No, my Lords, God forbid <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> I should. then we ſee, ſaid one of them, there is no ſuch matter, as vve vvere made to
<pb facs="tcp:150527:11"/> beleue. We were told, you were a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> young man, and willing to recant. but we ſee now, thou art a reſolute wilful fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and there is no remedie, but law muſt procede. I would be ſorie, my Lords, to geue your Lordships anie cauſe to thincke that euer I ment to recant knowing nothing wherin I haue offended, but only vttered my conſcience. If that be ſo great a matter of offence, let me haue lawe, in the name of Ieſus. Gods wil be done. Then ſpoke Iuſtice Dale, a Iuſtice of Peace; thou art a cogging coſening fellow, and getts thy lining, no man knoweth how, by cogging and lying. Sir, ſaid I, for my getting I nede not much to bragg of it, and for my lying and cogging you ſpeake of, I wold gladly you should know, that the Aunceſtres of the houſe, from whence I came, were gentlemen fiue hundred yeaes before your grandfather was Iuſtice. And ſo I ſtopped his mouth. And the Iudges committed me vnto my keper for that time. The next day being thurſday we went again to the Seſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at S. Margarits hil. Where about 2. of the clock in the afternone, I was called to the barr to be arayned. the Clerck ſayd: Iohn Rigbie hold vp thy hand, where beſeeching my ſwete Saviour Ieſus, our Bleſſed Ladie, and al the holie companie of Angels, and other Saincts to pray for me, I held vp my hand merily. So the Clerck read the Inditment,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:11"/> which when I had heard, I beſech you, my Lord, ſayd I, grant me libertie to ſpeake. anone you shall ſaid he. So I gaue place, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the reſt came to the barre, for we were ſix ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigned at that time together, fiue fellons, and my ſelf. About an houre after I vvas called again and bidden, hold vp my hand. which I did as before my Inditment was read again, and it was a sharp one. Then my Lord bad me ſpeake, and I anſwered to foure prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal points, briefly in this manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, my very good Lords, wheras I am charged in myn Inditment, that I was recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, it is very true; to God almightie I ſo was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I thinck lawfully might be. and as I remember, it is alſo allowed in your boke of common prayer, in the viſitation of the ſick, that if anie man find hymſelf burdened in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, he should make his confeſſion to the Miniſter. Which confeſſion manifeſteth a breach betwen God and his owne ſoule, and by this humble confeſſion he craueth pardon for his ſinnes, and reconciliation to God again by the hands of his Miniſter. Secondly wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I am charged, that I was reconciled from myn obedience to her Maieſtie, and to the Romish Religion: I wil depoſe the contrarie. For I was neuer reconciled from anie obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to my Prince, for I obey her ſtil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor to aine Religion: for although I ſomtimes went to Church againſt my wil, yet was I neuer of anie other Religion, then the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:12"/> and therfore neded no reconciliat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to Religion, vvhich I neuer ſtood againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thirdly, wheras (in my former anſwere; I ſaid, I went to Church, it is true, for feare of temporal punishment I ſo did, but neuer minded to fal from the old Religion, and therfore neded no reconciliation to Religion. Fourtly and laſtly I humbly beſech your good Lordships, as you wil anſwer it before God, to explicat the meaning of the ſtatute to the Iurie, if the meaning therof be, to make it treaſon, for a man fallen into the diſpleaſure of God, through his ſinnes, to be reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to God again by him, to whom God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the autoritie of reconciliation. If this be treaſon, Gods wil be done. Then ſaid both the Iudges, it was by à Romish Prieſt, and therfore treaſon. I anſwered, it vvas by a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Prieſt, who had the libertie of the priſon, and was frie for anie man to come vnto him, to releeue him: and therfore by the ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te no treaſon. Againe, my Lords, if it be not inquired of, within a yeare and a day, there can be no adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aganſt me by this ſtatute, if you wrong me not. Wherto replied one that ſat vnder the Iudges: Al this wil not ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy turne, for the Iurie muſt finde it treaſon. and ſo gaue them inſtructions, that it muſt needs be treaſon. Nay then Sir, ſaid I, if it muſt be, let it be. Gods wilbe done. Then ſaid Iuſtice Gaudie, Good Rigbie, I pray you thinck not in anie ſorte, I go about to ſeeke
<pb facs="tcp:150527:12"/> your death. her Maieſtie, and her lavves be merciful. If you wil yet conforme your ſelf, and ſay here, before the Iurie go forth, that you vvil go to Church, and ſubmit your ſelf, vve vvil procede no further. My Lord, ſaid I, if that be al the offence I haue committed, as I knovv it is; and if there be no other way but going to Church to helpe it, I would not vvish your Lordships to thincke, I haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> (as I hope) riſen thus manie ſteppes towards heauen, and novv vvil vvilfully let my foote ſlippe, and fal into the botomleſſe pit of hel. I hope in IESVS, he vvil ſtrengthen me, rather to ſuffer a thouſand deathes, if I had ſo manie liues to loſe. Let your lavv procede. Then ſaid the Iudge to the Iurie: you muſt <note place="margin">VVh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vvho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vvor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> quiſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vvh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> find t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> conſider of it, you ſee vvhat is ſaid: you cannot but find it treaſon by the Lavv. And ſo vvhen the reſt vvere arraigned, they vvent forth, and ſtood not long to thinck vpon the matter, but came againe, and I vvas called, and bidden againe hold vp my hand, they bad the Iurie looke on the priſoner, whether is he guiltie or no? and, who shal ſpeake for you? they al ſaid: the foreman. I beſech you, my Lord, ſaid I, may it pleaſe you to command ſilence, that I may heare my verdict. vvhich his Lordship did. but the foreman ſpake ſo ſoftly that I could not heare him. I willed him to ſpeake vp, and not to be afeard. Then he ſaid, Guiltie. To the which I ſaid, vvith a lowde voice, <hi>Laus tibi</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:13"/> 
               <hi>Domine Rex aeternae gloriae.</hi> And ſo went fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the barr. When the reſt were arraigned, and iudgement was to be giuen, I was firſt called<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Iuſtice Gaudy ſaid, what canſt thou ſay for thy ſelf, wherfore thou shouldeſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue iudgement of death? I anſwered, if that which before I ſaid, wil not ſerue, I can ſay no more. Good Rigbie, ſaid he, thinck not I ſeeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wil you yet go to Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No, my Lord. why then, ſaid he, iudgement <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> muſt paſſe. with a good wil, my Lord, ſaid I. Then he pronounced his ſentence, as you know the manner is. Which when he had ended, I ſaid, <hi>Deo gratias.</hi> al is but one death, my Lord, and aflea byting in compariſon of that, vvhich it pleaſed my ſvvete Sauiour IESVS, to ſuffer for my ſaluation. I humbly <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents God, faith Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thank your Lordship, for your great paines: and friely forgiue your Lordship, and this poore Iurie, and al other perſecutors in this cauſe vvho ſoeuer. Wel ſaid, ſaith he, in dede you shew your charitie. and then gaue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the reſt. And vvhen he had done he called vs together, and began his exhortation perſwading vs for our end. vvilling vs to ſend for a Miniſter, and prouide for death. I deſired his Lordship to ſpare my preſence, and beſtovv that counſail els vvhere. For I hope I am as vvel prouided, as by his exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation I should be. If you be, ſaid he, it is the better for you. God ſpede you vvel. and ſo vve parted. I pray God forgeue them al. and
<pb facs="tcp:150527:13"/> amend them, if it be his vvil. Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſto laudes, &amp; ſanctae Matri eius honor. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much he vvrit himſelf, after he vvas repriued: and ſent it, to a deare friend, vvho kepeth ſafe the original. For Iuſtice Gaudy vvho pronounced ſentence of death againſt him the fourth of March, cauſed him for that time, to be repriued. and ſo he continued priſoner in the vvhit Lion in Southvvork a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue three monethes more.</p>
            <p>On thurſday the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. of Iune, in the Aſſiſes holden at S. Magarets hil in Southvvorke, (Iuſtice Kingſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſitting vpon criminal cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Iuſtice Gaudy vpon ciuil matters and ſuites in Lavv, vvho in lent Aſſiſes before had the contrarie offices) M. Rigbie vvas produced again to the barre, and asked by Iuſtice Kingſmel vvhether he vvould yet go to the Church, or no? And he anſvvered (I thanck God) I am the ſame man that I vvas. It is not lavvful to go to your Church. I vvil <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> not go to it. Then thou muſt nedes dye, ſaith the Iuſtice, for longer repriue thou canſt not haue. he anſwered, my Lord, that is the thing vvhich I deſire, and looke for, but I thinck my ſelf farr vnvvorthie, to dye for ſo good a cauſe. The Iudge perceuing that he had no irons on his legges, being a condemned man, sharply rebuked the keper, and commanded a fine of fourtie shillings, for that default, to be ſet on his head: vvhervpon the keper
<pb facs="tcp:150527:14"/> brought a ſtrong payre of shackells. vvhich M. Rigbie taking into his handes, kneeling downe, and making the ſigne of the Croſſe, kiſſed them, and gaue them again to the keper, and ſo going vnto the blocke, the kepers man riuited them on very faſt on both his legges, and ſo they continued al that day, and the night folowing. The next day, being friday, he vvas broght again to the Seſſions houſe in the forenoone. VVhere after he had ſtoode a vvhile the irons fel from of his legges vpon the grounde. vvherat he ſmiled. the keper demanunding vvhy he ſmiled, he told him, his shackles vvere fallen of, and bad him ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite them on faſter, vvhich he did as he thought very ſure: but vvithin a litle ſpace they fel of again, vvhervpon he called again vpon his keper, and vvilled him to make them faſter. For I eſteme them, ſaid he, Iewells of to great pricè to be loſt. The kepers man, that had put them o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>twiſe before being much amazed, refuſed to do it againe. I wil faſten them no more, ſaid he, for I thinck it is not Gods vvil you should vveare anie irons. in ſo much that the keper com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded an other of his men to do it. And then Maiſter Rigbie remembring that à Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique maide in the priſon, called Mercie had that morning told him, that the night before she ſaw in her dreame, as she thought his irons fal of from his legges, ſaid to his keper, novv the maides dreame is found to be
<pb facs="tcp:150527:14"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue. and ſent alſo vvord therof to the maide from the Seſſions houſe. Moſt men that ſaw it, or haue heard of it, vndoubtedly thinck it to be miraculous. What the Iudges vvith the reſt of the bench, and others in authoritie thinck of it, is hard to iudge. They knew not be like them ſelues what to ſay. and therfore neither that day, nor afterwards ſpoke at al to the priſoner. but conſulted amongſt them ſelues, and vvith much difference of opinions, and often altering of ther purpoſes, at laſt one concluded, that which others misliked, that he muſt dye. In the meane time, returning that euening with his keper to the priſon, he vvas permitted to lodge in his accuſtomed cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. vvhere manie had before viſited him, being much delighted with his milde and ſwete conuerſation. And now manie more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted vnto the priſon to ſee him, vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of his irons ſo ſtrangely ſalling of his legges. Amongſt other things, a Catholique priſoner in the ſame houſe, dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of him, what he thought of that falling of, of his chaines. He anſwered, that he hoped, the bandes of his mortalitie should shortly be looſed. as in dede it proued. An other, conſidering that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times men of excellent corege, and reſolution of mind, do notvvithſtanding ſuſtaine great conflicts, betwen the ſoule and the bodie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the ſenſual part, asked him, how he felt him ſelfe? I am ſaid he, I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke our Lord, in very great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolation of mind.
<pb facs="tcp:150527:15"/> the reſidue of his time he ſpent likevvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vertous exerciſes, vvith great deuotion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> quent prayer, much abſtinence, watching and faſting, more and more, as his end drew ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaturday in the morning vvord vvas brought him, that he should dye that day. he anſvvered very cherf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly: <hi>Deo gratias.</hi> It is the beſt tydings that euer vvas broght me, of an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thing ſithence I vvas borne. ſo vvillingly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> beleued that vvhich he deſired. though moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men did not yet thinck it probable, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſons aforeſaid. For it is vvel knovve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and reported by ſuch as could tel, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iudges put his name twiſe in the Calenda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe that vvere to dye, and tvviſe ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againe the ſame day, before he vvas executed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For Iuſtice Gaudie endeuoring to repriue him lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, Iuſtice Kingſmel vrged, and vvould nedes haue him to dye. And in fine Iuſtice Gaudy ſeenig his inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> croſſed by Kingſmel, vvho the third time put his name in that calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar agane, and ſo deliuered it vp amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thoſe vvhich should dye, turned himſelf from the companie, and vvas by ſome ſene to vvepe. This vncertentie, eſpecially the Calendar being brought to the keper, his name leaft out, after it had bene tvviſe ſent for, and altered, deceiued manie of his frends, vvho had a purpoſe, to haue bene preſent at his death, had they not thus bene perſwaded to thinck vndoubtedly, that he vvas againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:15"/>
            <p> The ſame day the Miniſter of Saint George his Church, adioyning to the priſon, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Maiſter Rigbie, he curtously ſaluted him and asked vvho he vvas. The Miniſter ſaid, I am parſon of Saint Georges parish: and hearnig you are this day to dye, am come by commandement to confer vvith you, and to inſtruct you. I thanke you, ſaid M. Rigbie, for your paines. but vve tvvo are oppoſite in Religion. Therfore I am not to conferre vvith you in matters of faith. I haue long looked <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> for death, I am prepared, fully reſolued, and moſt readie to offer vp my life for ſo vvorthie a cauſe. The miniſter benig hervpon about to depart, Maiſter Rigbie tooke him by the hand, and very courtously toke leaue vvith him ſaing: Fare you vvel Sir. I pray God make you a good man.</p>
            <p>Betvvixt fiue and ſix of the clocke in the afternone M. Cheeke, one of the vndershrifs officiers, comming to the priſon, called for M. Iohn Rigbie, ſaing they ſtaid for him. He anſvvered, I am readie for you, good M. Cheeke. May it pleaſe you to ſtay but a very little vvhile, and I come. Ad ſo haſtening he vvent moſt ſweetly and curtously to ſalute, and take his leaue of his felovv Catholique priſoners, and other fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des then preſent vvith him: vvho al vvith great reſpect (as to one going to poſſeſſe a Kingdom, for revvard of his faithful ſeruice) euerie one humbly kneeled vnto him, and he vvith like reſpect to
<pb facs="tcp:150527:16"/> them, as to Gods deſigned Martyrs, alſo kne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led: and to their great conſolation imbraced, and ſaluted euerie one of them with a kiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of peace. In which deuout manner leauing them, and deſiring their charities, to aſſiſt him in this his iourney, tovvards his owne country, with their deuout prayers, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them that he wold remember them (as they requeſted) in his aſſuredly. Then going downe into the yarde, he found the hurdle at the ſtayers foote redie prepared. Where he kneling downe, and firſt ſigning himſelf with the ſigne of the Croſſe, framed himſelf to ſay ſome prayer. but preſently one Maiſter More, the vndershrifs deputie, interrupted him. and he riſing ſmot his hand vpon the horſe, merily ſaing, Go thy vvayes, this is the ioyfuleſt day that euer I knevv. And ſigning himſelf again with the ſigne of the Croſſe, laid himſelf gently downe vpon the hurdle, vvith great alacritie of minde, as wel appeared by his ſvvete Angelical conte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. vvhich the ſtanders by curiously ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, ſome asked him, if he laughed from his hart, he anſwered? yes verily from my hart. And beare vvitnes vvith me, al good people, that I am now forthvvith to giue my life only for the Catholique cauſe. Maiſter More taking exceptions ſaid, No Maiſter Rigbie, you dye for treaſon in the higheſt degree, for being reconcilid by a Seminarie
<pb facs="tcp:150527:16"/> Prieſt. Yes Maiſter More, ſaid he again, for neither can that be treaſon. nor yet I dye not for that only. For as you knovv the Iudge offered me oftentimes to ſaue my life, for only going to Church. Then pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his hat downe to shadovv his eyes, bad them, In the name of our Lord go on. and ſo ſetled himſelf to his deuotions. But they making a litle ſtaye, he ſaid me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: vvhen go you? I think your horſe is not able to draw me. At vvhich vvords they vvent forvvard, and he fel vnto his prayers.</p>
            <p>In the vvay tovvards the place of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, called S. Thomas Watering, came ryding as was thought two courtiers. but shortly one of them was knowne to be the Earle of Rutla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and the other was Captaine Whytlock in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie. they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming nere the hurdle, and viewing the priſoner, the Captaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him, vvhat he vvas, of vvhat yeares, and what might by the cauſe of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation to this kind of death? M. Rigbie looking vp, and hearing ſome name the Earle of Rutland, ſuppoſing the Captaine to be the Earle, tooke of his hat and deſired his honor humbly to pardon him, in being ſo vndutiful as to haue bene covered in his preſence, for I knew not (ſaid he) of ſuch honorable aſse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie. and to your queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may it like your honour, my name is Iohn Rigbie, a poore gentleman, of the houſe of Harrock in Lancashire: my ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:17"/> about thirtie yeares, my iudgement and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> demnation to this death, is only and merely for that I anſvvered the Iudge, that I vvas re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled; and for that I refuſed to go vnto the Church, to heare the English seruice. Wherat the Captanine ſeemed to meruel: and ſaid, ſure it is very ſtrange, that anie man should be put to death for that. vndoubtedly, ſaid the priſoner, it is for no other cauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doe aſſure you. The Captaine vvished hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to doe, as the Quene vvould haue him (that is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> to go to the Proteſtants Church) and turni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to the Shri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s deputie, conferred vvith hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about the matter. After a little ſpace th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Earle and the Captain rode againe to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hurdle, and cauſing it a little to be ſtayd, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> captaine ſaid, are you a maried man, or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No ſir, ſaid he, I am a bacheler; and (in ſmiling wiſe) more then that, I am a maide. that is much, ſaid the Captain, for a man of your yeares, you haue it ſeemeth ſtriuen much againſt your owne flesh. M. Rigbie anſvvered, I vvould be loath to ſpeake anie thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the truth, I am in dede a maide. and that is more then I neded to ſay. The Captain concluded: Then I ſee, thou haſt vvorthily deſerued a virgins crowne. I pray God ſend the the Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heauen, and that thou maiſt do vvel: I deſire thee, pray for me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo they rid to the place of execution, not ſpeaking anie more to him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and vvhen the officiers vvere readie to turne him of the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:17"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rt, the Earle and the Captain poſted avvay, much aſtonished at his courege and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie.</p>
            <p>The Captain often related theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and vvithal added that he had ſeene manie dye, but neuer had, nor should ſee the like to him: for modeſtie, patience, and vndoubted reſolution in his Religion. And that it vvold not be good for our ſtate, to put ſuch men to death.</p>
            <p>Novv the priſoner being in place, to end this tragedie, the officiers brought him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hurdle to the cart. vvhere he kneled dovvne and ſaid the Parer noſter, Aue Maria, Credo, and Confiteor al alovvde, vntil he came to thoſe vvordes, <hi>the holie Apostls S. Peter and Saint Paule,</hi> wherat the ruder ſort of the people exclamed, that he prayed to Saints. and ſo he vvas not permitted to come to the end. The executione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> helping him vp into the cart, he gaue him an angel of gold, ſaing: here take this in token that I friely forgiue thee, and al others, that haue bene acceſſarie to my death. Thou shalt haue more, a poore ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of fuſtian, and a new shert vvhich I put on this morning. I vvould it vvere better for thee. Then taking of his hat, he threw it from him. And making the ſigne of the Croſſe, he vewed the multitude (vvhich vvas very great) rovvnd about him. And vvith cherful contenance holding his handes before his breaſt, vvith his eyes cloſed, he meditated a litle while.
<pb facs="tcp:150527:18"/> And after looking vp, ſemed to make cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance to ſome of his freinds in the preſſe. The executioner in the meane time vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his garters. himſelfe vntruſſed his points<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that ſo nimbly, as the beholders merue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, to ſee a man in ſuch caſe, ſo quick and actiue, and nothing diſmade for death ſo nere approching. Taking alſo his falling band from his neck, he rowled it on a heape, and caſt it from him, as farre as he could. Wherupo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome ſaid: that wil be taken vp for a Reliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. His clothes being taken of al to his shert, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hangman offered to put the halter ouer h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> head, which he ſtayed, taking it betwixt bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his handes, ſo kiſſed it, and gaue it to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againe ſaying: Now do your pleaſure with it. And preſently he put it ouer his head. Beginning then to ſpeake to the people, More the vndershrifes deputie bade him pray for the Quene, which he did very affectionatly, as might appeare to come from a charitable, and loyal hart. The deputie asked him: What Traitors knoweſt thou in England? If thou knoweſt anie reueale them. God is my witnes, ſaid he, I know none. VVat! ſaith the deputie again, if he vvil confeſſe nothing, driue avvay the cart. VVhich vvas donne ſo ſudainly, that he could neither ſpeake to the people: nor recommend his ſoule againe to God, as he vvas about to do. Again the depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie very shortly commanded the hangman to do his dutie: meaning that he should cut the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:18"/> rope, and let him fal downe, vvhich vvas ſo incontinently done, that he ſtood vpright vpon his feete, like to a man a litle amazed, til the butchering fellovves claſping about him, by maine force threvv him on the ground. Where coming againe perfectly to himſelfe, he ſaid alovvd and diſtinctly: God forgeue you. Ieſus receiue my ſoule. And immediatly an other cruel felovv ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by (who was no officer at al, but a common porter) ſet his foote vpon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs throte, and ſo held him dovvne, that he could not ſpeake anie more. VVherof the ſame felovv made great vaunt, and boſted aftervvards, vntil ſome of the more ciuil people, reprehending him for his bad mind, and hard hart, he began to be ashamed of his fact, and denied it to others, that char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him thervvith. Others held his arme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and legges whiles the executioner diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and vnbovveled him. And vvhen he felt them pulling out his hart, he vvas yet ſo ſtrong, that he thruſt the men from him, which held his armes. Finally they cut of his head, and diuided his quarters, diſpoſing of them in ſeueral places about Southvvork, as is accuſtomed. The people going avvay mutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much at the crueltie vſed in the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And generally al ſortes bevvayled his death.</p>
            <p>Thus you haue a plaine and ſincere narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s death, and of the cauſe therof. Which vvas, as you ſee, for being reconciled
<pb facs="tcp:150527:19"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to go to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Church. For he vvas in dede condemned fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the one, and executed for the other. Now whether either of theſe, or both together be treaſon; or may truly be ſo called; is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> principal queſtion of controuerſie, touching this mans and other Catholiques ſuffering in our countrie.</p>
            <p>For reſolution wherof, if but in England it ſelfe, the greateſt number of voices of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> English perſons (ſuppoſing that al durſt and would ſpeake that they think) might decide the matter, there were no great doubt, but the verdict would be clere and abſolute, for the Catholiques in this behalfe. For not onlie Catholiques themſelues, which (God be thanked) are a very great number: but alſo moſt Proteſtants, and in maner al Puritanes, and ſome others of diuers other ſects, take theſe facts of Catholiques to be mere mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of conſcience, and voide of al treaſon: and but thoſe few onlie, in whoſe handes the gouernment of the Realme now ſpecially conſiſteth, with a few more that folow the ſway of authoritie, do hold or profeſſe the contrarie opinion. Or els if the whole ſtate of the land, of former times, from our firſt conuerſion to Chriſt, to theſe late yeares: Or finally if the whole Chriſtian world, both of times paſt and preſent might be Iudge (as by al reaſon it should) then ſentence would eaſely be for vs, and al further diſpute
<pb facs="tcp:150527:19"/> would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. For neither in England before our dayes; nor els where before nor as yet in al Chriſtendom; no not in thoſe other places which are alſo diuided from the Roman Church, is there anie ſuch opinion holden nor ſuch lawes made, that to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, or abſolued from ſinnes by a Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Prieſt, should be treaſon, but only in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, within theſe laſt 40. yeares. For albeit in Geneua, and in ſome parts of Germanie, as alſo in Holland, and ſome other like places, they punish with leſſe penalties, ſuch as go to Confeſſion, heare Maſſe, or otherwiſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe the Catholique Religion: yet none ſuch are in anie of thoſe places eſtemed nor iudged Traitors, nor bereued of their liues for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. Neither are anie punished at al, but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in England for refuſing to ſweare, that they think in their conſcience that the King, Quene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Prince, is and ought to be ſupreme head, or ſupreme gouernour of the Church, immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnder Chriſt, in al cauſes as wel ſpiritual as temporal. For asking, or receuing anie maner of diſpenſation, indulgence, or other grace of the Sea Apoſtolique. For hauing an Agnus Dei, Beades, Graines, Croſſes, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dails, Images, Pictures, or other things, bleſſed by the Bishop of Rome. For per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading anie perſon to be a member of the Catholi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Roman Chruch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or hauing autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ſubordinat to the ſame Roman Chruch, to abſolue from ſinnes. For being made
<pb facs="tcp:150527:20"/> Prieſt in anie English College or Seminarie without the Realme, and ſo returning into their countrie. And for the like things enacted and made as heynous crimes by new Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lawes. Al which pertaine directly, and euidently to Gods ſpecial Seruice, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, Sacraments, ſpiritual regiment, reliefe and health of ſoules. And ſo are matters of Religion, moſt really diſtinct in nature and ſubſtance, from matters of temporal ſtate; and much more from treaſon, and from al diſobedience to temporal Princes. Whoſe Soueraigntie, and ſecuritie both is and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hath benne moſt ſpecially maintained and neuer oppugned by the Catholique Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For euen as Chriſt him ſelfe and his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Apoſtles, and their perpetual Succeſſors yelded, and taught al men to yeld tribute, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> obedience, and al dutifid honour and ſeruice to temporol Powres and Princes, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently <note place="margin">Tim.</note> to pray for al ſuch both publikly and priuatly: ſo al Catholiques in England, and euery where continually do the ſame. And namely this holie Martyr (as appeareth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 32</note> acknowledged and yelded al temporal powre, and authoritie to the Quene, ſtil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing and behauing him ſelfe as a faithful and loyal ſubiect, ſeruing her, and praying for her, and euen to death denying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting al treaſons and travtors. How wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully therfore he was conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to death, may ſufficiently appeare by that which hath benne
<pb facs="tcp:150527:20"/> here ſaid. Firſt becauſe the Lawes or ſtatutes pretended againſt him, are not ſufficient La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves, wherby to condemne him, depending wholly vpon falſe and vnlawful groundes, if in dede he had benne of an other Religion before, and afterwards reconciled to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique. Secondly becauſe his proper caſe was ſuch, that by the ſame ſtatutes he could not be conuinced, as him ſelfe very wel decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at his arraignment. Neither by the ſtatutes <note place="margin">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> againſt reconciliation, for that he was alwayes in faith a Catholique, and therfore neded not reconciliation to anie Religion, nor was ſo reconciled, but only abſolued from his ſinnes committed of frailtie. Nor by the <note place="margin">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſtatute aganſt receiuing or releuing Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Prieſts; becauſe the Prieſt that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued him, had at that time ſo much liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in priſon, that al men that vvould might come to him and releue him. And much leſſe is there anie thing at al in that ſtatute pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting anie man to be temporally or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually releued by him. But al their accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proofes failing, the Iudges alſo and the whole bench being ſilent, and moſt men expecting that the priſonner should be quit, and frie from ſentence of death, then came in the comon vnderſong <hi>(the fauburden of ſuch tragical pagents)</hi> from a companion that ſat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſaying; <hi>Al this wil not ſerue thy turne; for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>the Iurie muſt finde it treaſon. If it muſt be</hi> (ſaith fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the happie martyr) <hi>let it be. Gods wil be</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:21"/> 
               <hi>done.</hi> And ſo I wil ſay no more in a matter ſo clere, touching the pretenſed cauſe of his condemnation to death.</p>
            <p>It reſteth only, to ſpeake a vvord or tvvo more of his refuſal to go to the Proteſtants Church. Which as it vvas the particular cauſe, that the ſaid ſentence vvas geuen, ſo vvas it alſo the principal cauſe that the ſame vvas put in execution: for othervviſe either it had not bene pronounced, or had bene remitted or annullated, if at anie of tenne or twelue times, vvhen it vvas publikly vrged vnto him, he vvould haue yelded therto.</p>
            <p>And firſt it is a thing certaine and euident, that this refuſing or omitting to be preſent, at the publique Seruice of a contrarie Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is no vvhere els ſo greuouſly punished, as now in Englad. For the Catholique Church to beginne vvith al (becauſe her aduerſaries count her very ſeuere) is ſo farre from vrging or forcing, thoſe that be not Catholiques, to be preſent at Maſſe, Matines, or at anie pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Office in the Church, that she aloweth none ſuch at al to enter in, nor to abide there, though they should deſire it. And hath for this purpoſe a ſpecial Order of Clergie men, vvho are called <hi>Ostiarij;</hi> vvhoſe office is to admite only the obedient children of the Church, and to kepe out, or driue out al others. And if by ignorance, force, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe, anie that ought not, happen to be there, incontinently as the ſame is perceiued, the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:21"/> Sacrifice, and al other publique Offices do ceaſe, til they be got out againe. In other places, eſpecially in the moſt partes of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, ſtraict Lavves be ordayned, that none shal be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to anie practiſe, or outward conformitie in anie other Religion, then them ſelues like and alow of. and that al perſons may friely, vvithout impechment or moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vſe that Religion, vvhich in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences they hold to be beſt, and moſt auala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for their ſoules health. Wherby innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſons of diuers Religions, notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their diuerſitie of opinions in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith, and their daylie frequenting of diuers Aſſemblies in diſtinct Churches, liue and conuerſe together, ech one according to his profeſſion, trade, and traffike, in al peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quiet maner. Only in England, and in few other places, the Catholique Rites, Offices, and eſpecially the Sacrifice are prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited: and a certaine conformitie, or external shew, is required and exacted (in euerie prouince, countrie, or kingdom diuerſly, as their doctrines be diuers) vpon ſmaller, or vpon greater penalties. Which in England are more and more augmented theſe later yeares. For vvheras in the beginning of the <note place="margin">An. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eliz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Quenes raigne, it was prohibited to ſay or heare Maſſe, vnder the paine either of paying an hundreth Markes, or els of ſuffering ſix monethes impriſomnent: in a latter ſtatute, the price or penaltie is increaſed; that vvho <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:22"/> ſoeuer heareth Maſſe, muſt both ſuffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> vvhole yeares impriſonment, and alſo pay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hundreth Markes. And he that ſaith Maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt be committed to the next Gaole, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vvhole yeare, and alſo pay tvvo hundreth markes; or els remaine in the Gaole, vntil he shal pay it. And if he be a Ieſuite, or a <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 27.</note> Seminarie Prieſt, then both he, and thoſe that intertained him, muſt al dye for it. The Prieſt as a traitor, the other as fellons. Again vvheras in the ſaid former ſtatute, al perſons aboue the age of xvi. yeares are commanded to be preſent at their new forme of ſeruice <hi>(brought in place of the Catholique Office, and Sacrifice at the ſame time abolished)</hi> euerie Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and Holie day, vpon paine of paying xij pence for euerie dayes abſence: the ſame is not only augmented in the other ſtatute (to a farre greater price, then Chriſtians pay for vſe of their Religion in Conſtantinople) to xx. poundes for euerie monethes abſence from their Church: but alſo vvithout ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, Chriſtians in a Chriſtian Realme (vvhich is much to be pitied and iuſtly vvondered at) are finally perſecuted to death, for not committing an act, and a ſinne againſt their conſcience. As vvas manifeſt in this bleſſed Martyr, and in manie others. Who if they would but haue yelded in this one point, should not haue dyed, for al their other ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed treaſons.</p>
            <p>But if anie man wil yet doubt, or ſeme to
<pb facs="tcp:150527:22"/> meruel, why this Martyr (and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manie others) would not in al this longe combate, being ſo of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en and ſo earneſtly vrged therto, ſaue his life by once ſaying he would go to the Church: himſelf plainly and publikly anſwered the Iudges, and the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 16. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 12.</note> vvhole vvorld, that he could not do it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he should by ſo doing, <hi>not haue ſaued but haue loſt his life.</hi> and therfore <hi>he loſt it in this world, and ſo found life euerlaſting.</hi> Rightly conſidering that better it was, to fal into the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 13.</note> cruel handes of men, then into the iuſt vvrath of God almightie. Who is a ieliouſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 20. <hi>ſequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> God, that neither vvil ſuffer his people to ſerue other gods, nor him ſelfe to be ſerued in other maner, then by Moyſes, and by his other high Prieſts he hath apointed. VVherof (beſides manie others) vve haue a moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nu.</hi> 1.</note> example in the people of the Iewes, that did not ſeuer them ſelues, from the Tabernacles of the impious, as they were commanded, but yelded to the Oppoſites of Moyſes, and vvere invvrapped in their ſinnes. And ſo not only Core, Dathan, and Abiron, the heades and ringleaders, vvith their vviues, children, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinewes, vvere ſwallowed vp in the gaping earth, deſcending aliue into hel; and their tvvo hundreth and fiſteie complices and cooperators, al deuoured vvith fire from heauen: but alſo their other adherents, and partners in the ſchiſme, to the number
<pb facs="tcp:150527:23"/> of fourtene thouſand ſeuen hundreth of the people, perished in like ſorte by the ſame fire: vvhich ceaſed not deuouring thoſe that had anie way participated in the ſame reuolt, til Aaron ſent by Moyſes, had apeazed the vvrath of God, vvith Sacrifice and other prayers. And shal we think that the ſame God vvil not as iuſtly and ſeuerly, either in this vvorld or in the next, punish vs Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, if vve ioyne our ſelues in profeſſion, or practiſe of a contrarie Religion, to that which Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors taught and obſerued, and vvhich our countrie vvas firſt conuerted vnto? No aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly. For he is the ſame iuſt God ſtil, to Iewes and to Gentils, to Iſrailits and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; <hi>Ieſus Christ yeſterday, and today, the ſame</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>for euer.</hi> Who commandeth vs, not only not to beleue thoſe that shal ſay: <hi>Loe here is Chriſt or there:</hi> but alſo <hi>not to go out,</hi> of the felowship of al nations chriſtned, into one corner, tovvne, or countrie: as S. Auguſtin vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cle.</hi> 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi>
               </note> that place. And the Apoſtle admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisheth vs the ſame, more at large: <hi>No ſocietie</hi> (ſaith he) nor felowship: <hi>no agreement, no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation, no conſent</hi> can be betvven Chriſt and Belial; and none ought to be, in the publique prayers, nor in aſſemblies for the ſeruice of God, betvven Catholiques and vvho ſo euer of contrarie Religion. <hi>Go out of the middes of them, and ſeparate yourſelues:</hi> ſaith our Lord, <hi>and touch not the vncleane, and I wil receiue you.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:23"/> And contrariwiſe at the laſt day, <hi>he wil bring</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124.</note> 
               <hi>thoſe that decline into obligations</hi> (for loue or for feare of the world) <hi>with the workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> as teſtifieth the Royal Prophet. Who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe admonisheth vs in an other Pſalme by his owne example, or rather in the perſon of euerie faithful ſoule, ſaying: <hi>With</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>them that do vuiuſt things, I wil not enter in. I haue hated the Church of the malignant: and with the impious I wil not ſit.</hi> And the Prophet Elias crieth vnto ſuch as vvould ſerue both God <note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and his enimie: <hi>How long halt you on two wayes, if our Lord be God, folow him: but if Baal, folow him.</hi> Good Tobias a youth in captiuitie, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tob.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> vvould not go (as manie did) to Ieroboams golden calues, but fleeing their compagnies vvent to Ieruſalem, to the Temple of our Lord, and there adored. The three children Sidrach, Miſach, and Abdenago in the like captiuitie, fearing God more then men, anſvvered boldly, <hi>Be it knowne to thee ô King,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>that we worship not thy God, and we adore not the golden ſtatue, which thou haſt erected.</hi> Old Eleaza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus <note place="margin">2. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6.</note> would not eate, nor ſeme to eate ſwines flesh, againſt the law; but rather choiſe a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious death, then a weriſome or hateful life, if by diſſimulation in ſo religious a cauſe, he should haue procured damnation to his owne ſoule, and alſo eternal ruine of manie more by his example. Read alſo the hiſtorie of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ca:</hi> 7</note> mother and her ſeuen ſonnes, al martyred for the ſame cauſe. And generally the Iewes did <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:24"/> not conuerſe, nor communicate vvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Samaritanes in ſpiritual affayres; vvhoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cuſtome herein our Sauiour approueth, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> geueth expreſſe ſentence for the Ievves in this behalfe; and that the right adoration, and ſaluation was of the Ievves part. Becauſe they had good ground for their Temple in Ieruſalem, and the Samaritanes none at al. for their worshiping in Gariſin. An other general rule our Sauiour geueth, <hi>He that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> 
               <hi>is not with me, is againſt me; and he that gethereth not with me ſcattereth.</hi> VVherupon S. Ierome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 58. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amaſ.</hi>
               </note> proueth, that al they do ſcatter, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ther not vvith the reſt of the Church, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> particularly that gether not vvith the chief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Paſtor therof, ſucceding Sainct Peter. To the ſame effect the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>you can not drink the Chalice of our Lord, and the Chalice of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>diuels: you can not be partakers of the table of our Lord, and of the table of diuels.</hi> And to ſuch <hi>Neuters</hi> as vvould ſerue al turnes he crieth: <hi>Beare not the yoke with infidels. for what partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>hath iuſtice with iniquitie, what ſocietie is there betwen light and darknes;</hi> finally, <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols?</hi> And vvhat be the Idols that novv moleſt the Church (ſaith S. Ierome) but Hereſies? <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mos. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ab.</hi> 2. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> VVherfore al that looke to haue feloship with Chriſt and his members in his bodie and blood, muſt flie from the feloship of al infidels, and abſtaine from al partipici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation in cauſes of Religion, vvith thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:150527:24"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat haue erected an other Altar or table, or that haue erected a contrarie forme of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eruing God, againſt the Altar and Sacrifice of Chriſt, and his Catholique Church. And in novviſe conforme them ſelues to theſe nevv procedings, by going to their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, vvhich is <hi>the proper marke of their ſocietie.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apot.</hi> 13.</note> And therfore moſt conſtantly refuſed by this glorious Martyr, ſo manfully fighting this good fight. wherby himſelfe hath ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued a Crovvne of glorie; God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie is ſpecially glorified; his Saintes highly honored; Catholiques much edified, and comforted; and the Proteſtants greatly ashamed and confounded. <hi>Our Lord graunt al</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. 128.</note> 
               <hi>thoſe, may be</hi> frutfully <hi>ashamed,</hi> happilly <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and</hi> quikly <hi>turned back, that</hi> novv <hi>hate Sion.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. BRIEF</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:25"/>
            <head>A. BRIEF MENTION<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> NINE OTHER MARTYRS, AN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certaine other Catholiques perſecuted for the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cauſe, this ſame yeare, With an answer to our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries obiection, of diſcord amongſt Catholiques.</head>
            <p>AT York in Lent laſt was arraigned M. Chriſtopher Wharton Prieſt, Maiſter of Art of the Vniuerſitie of Oxford, ſuſpected and accuſed to be a Seminarie Prieſt. and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon indicted of hiegh treaſon, for returni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> into England, contrarie to the ſtatute ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the yeare of our Lord, 1585. Who w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An. Reg. Eliz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>M. Robert Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. Io. Sands. W. Tom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. Ro. Debdal. Ed. Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den. Hugh. Tailor. Thur. Hunt. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> in dede made Prieſt at Rhemes by the Cardinal of Guiſe (of Bleſſed memorie) the laſt day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> March. 1584. (As alſo 30. other Englishmen receaued holie Orders the ſame time with him of which diuerſe be now alſo Martyrs) Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles he confeſſed no more but that he was a Prieſt, before the ſaid ſtatute was made: lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it to his accuſers to proue when he was made. For he being about the age of thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcore years, might wel (by diſpenſation) haue bene made Prieſt in rhe reigne of Q. Marie, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the feaſt of the Natiuitie of S. Iohn Baptiſt, in the firſt yeare of this Quene, and ſo out of the danger of this new ſtatute. Manie odious things were obiected and amplified (as their cuſtome is) againſt the Pope, Cardinals, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt of England, Ieſuits and Seminarie Prieſts, charging them with Idolatrie, Superſtition, much falſe doctrine; with Treaſon againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:25"/> Quene and Realme, and with diſſentions alſo betwen Ieſuits and Seminarie Prieſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> al falſe and impious ſclanders; as he plainly told them; nothing at al pertaining to the Indictme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his liefe depended) about the time when he was made Prieſt. Concerning which point after a few vncertaine coniectures were alleaged which agreed il, and proued nothing againſt him: vpon the onlie teſtimonie of M. Sauil, Baron of the exchequer (who was alſo his Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge) affirming that he knew him in Oxford, ſome years after the time mentioned in the new ſtatute; and then not taken for a Prieſt: he was denounced, Guiltie, and condemned to death as for hiegh Treaſon. And a graue Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Matron was alſo indicted of felonie, and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned to death, for receiuing him into her houſe. As if she alſo had knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford to haue bene no Prieſt, and afterwards ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Prieſt, who knewe him not at al, but a ſmal time before he was taken in her houſe. Finally after earneſt perſwation to go to their Church, which she vtterlie refuſed, she receaued her Croune of Martyrdome, according to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, whoſoeuer <hi>receaueth a prophet, in the name of a prophet, shal receaue the reward of a prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit there ſemed leſſe probabilitie to peruert the venerable Prieſt, yet they omitted not to vrge vnto him the vſual tentation; that if he would go to their Church, he might injoy both liefe and libertie; and be praeferred alſo amongſt them. Al which he conſtantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned
<pb facs="tcp:150527:26"/> in reſpect of Gods honour, his ovvn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaluation, and edification or deſtruction of manie by his example. And ſo in Eaſter vveke the 28. of March he alſo receiued his glorious croune. And to their other impertinent talke (both before and after his ſentence) he alſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered briefly, that in the Catholique Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Religion (which he profeſſed, and for vvhich he was readie to dye) there is neither Idolatrie, nor-Superſtition, nor falshoode, nor contrarietie of doctrin. And though there be diſſentions ſomtimes amongſt Catholiques, either Prieſts or others, yet thoſe differences are not in Articles of their faith, but in other matters, of ſome particular Iuriſdiction, right or title, ſpiritual or temporal, and the like. And that for his ovvne part he had no ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie vvith anie Catholique, nor breach of charitie vvith any perſon liuing vvhoſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Which was for him, at that time, a very ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient anſwer. And much hath bene ſaid, and vvritten alſo theſe late yeares, of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and vnitie of the Catholique doctrin. Neuertheleſſe here it shal not be amiſſe (gentle reader) to adde ſomwhat more in explication of his anſwer, touching the differences riſſen amongſt ſome English Catholiques, vvhich our Aduerſaries ſo reprochfully obiect to al. For albeit, the perfect are neuer ſcandalized; yet the vveake often are; and ſome do miſtake <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>v.</hi> 165.</note> the caſe; and ſome doubtles are guiltie of great fault, in making or in nourishing this debate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:26"/>
            <p> Al which wil be more clere; if firſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind the ſtate of Catholiques, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this controuerſie begane; vve then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider vvhence it proceded; vvherin it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth; and betvven vhom it is.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe it ſemeth neceſſarie, that we beginne from the laſt general reuolt, from the Catholique Religion in our Countrie; Which vvas in the firſt yeare of this Quenes raigne. For she comming to the Croune in the end of the yeare 1558. vvithin few mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes after a Parliament vvas called, vvherin vtterly aganſt the vvilles of al the Lords ſpiritual (auouching that they did not, nor vvould not conſent to change the ſtate of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) the Lords temporal and Commons tooke vpon them, and <hi>de facto</hi> pretended, to abolish al authoritie or Iuriſdiction of the Bishop of Rome in England: abandoned the holie Sacrifice of Maſſe, and other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Offices: and in place therof reſtored the nevv forme of Seruice inſtituted in the ſecond yeare of K. Edvvard the ſixt, but augmented, <hi>altered, and corrected</hi> (for ſo they ſpeake) and further in moſt peremptorie and arrogant manner, did <hi>in Gods name</hi> (but vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out commiſſion from God) <hi>earnestly require and charge al the Archbishops Bishops and other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries,</hi> that they should indeuour themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to the vttermoſt of their knovvledges, to ſee the ſame put in execution; threatening them vvith Gods vvrath and punishinent,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:27"/> 
               <hi>if this good and wholſome Law</hi> (for ſooth) <hi>were neglected.</hi> Al which holie Bishops obeying God, rather then men; vvere preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly depriued of their Bishopriques, and al other conſtant Clergimen of their ſpiritual liuings, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices; Heretiques, or ſuch as yelded to the parctiſe of Hereſie, put in their places. And diuerſe alſo of the Laitie sharply punished, for not conforming themſelues to theſe nevv procedings. In which ſtate though the ſame Catholique Prelates ſtil kept their titles and right, aſ vvel of their dignities, as of their holie functions (which could by no meanes be taken from them) yet did they not exerciſe any publique Iuriſdiction; but expecting better times, al the Bishops, and moſt of the old clergie haue ended their liues in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, banishment, or in other poore ſtate, al more or leſſe reſtrained and perſecuted. Wherby the Eccleſiaſtical Ierarchie of the Church of England, for lack of ſucceſſion of ordinarie ſpiritual Paſtors, did vvholy decay and ceaſe; yet continually there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome conſtant Catholiques, and ſome few Catholique Prieſts, which miniſtred the holie Sacraments, and ſupplied in priuat and ſecret ſorte, other neceſſarie Offices vvithout anie ſubordination of one to an other vvithin the Realme; the Sea Apoſtolique graunting <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> facultie, to the worthie Confeſſor, the Bishop of Lincolne and others, to ſubdelegate ſuch as vvere found fit to heare Confeſſions, and
<pb facs="tcp:150527:27"/> to abſolue, alſo in Caſes reſerued, as nede should require. And furthermore this good ſeede of Catholique Religion conſerued by Gods goodnes, vvas alſo vvel vvatered, and proſpered much by ſundrie good bookes, written by diuerſe learned and zealous men, in defence of the Catholique faith. wherby not only theſe Reliques vvere confirmed and ſtayed therein, but ſome alſo conuerted from ſchiſme and hereſie. But in the firſt tene years moſt men ſtil hoping of a change, or tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, litle induſtrie vvas vſed, for making more Prieſts, to ſerue our countrie in this greate deſolation: til the renovvmed Doctor Allen, (aftervvards Cardinal) moſt prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreſeing the great defect of a ſucceſſion of Prieſts, vvithout vvhom no Sacrament could be duly adminiſtred, no Sacrifice offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and conſequently no Religion long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, but al turne to Hereſie, Apoſtaſie, and Atheiſme, found meanes (by Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial prouidence) in the yeare of our Lord 1568. to erect in the vniuerſitie of Doway with the approbation of Pius Quintus, a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of English ſtudents; vvho by yelding themſelues to Collegial diſcipline, and to a ſet forme and courſe of ſtudie, with public; exerciſe, might attaine more vertue, zeale and knovvledge, and ſo be made Prieſts, and returne into their Countrie; as aboue foure hundred haue ſince donne, to the infinite good of manie thouſand ſoules, from this
<pb facs="tcp:150527:28"/> one Mother College, not only the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the English nation, but (as vve take it) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> firſt in Chriſtendome, inſtituted after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forme of Seminarie Colleges, appointed to be erected, by the holie Councel of Trent, in al Catholique Prouinces, for the better education, and perpetual ſucceſſion of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giemen</p>
            <p>The good reporte and euident proofe of vvhoſe profitable indeuours eaſily moued our holie father Pope Gregorie the thirtenth, to indue the ſame College, vvith a monethlie exhibition or penſion, in the yeare 1575. For before that time, it had no other Reuenevves but the ſtipend of Doctor Allen their Preſident and Founder, being one of the kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Vniuerſitie, and vvhat more he procured of other Benefactors. Which ſo continued, til the tumults of the Lovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countries, and povver of the Rebels did grovv ſo great, that in the yeare 1578. by the working of the Quene and Counſel of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, with the Prince of Orenge, and his confederats, the ſaid College vvas driuen from Dovvay, and ſo remoued to Rhemes in France. VVhere ſtil it proſpered, much contrarie to the expectation of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutores. Yea moreouer (marke ye here the great mercie of God tovvards the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of our Nation) the ſame yeare our ſaid holie father Pope Gregorie founded an other
<pb facs="tcp:150527:28"/> English College in Rome; that there might be tvvo ſuch nourceries of Clergimen for our Countrie, committing the gouernment therof, to the moſt exquiſite Order, that the chriſtian vvorld novv hath, for education of youth (eſpecially for ſuch an Apoſtolical purpoſe as this is) to the holie Societie of IESVS. VVhich charge ſo laid vpon them, vvas to the ſingular ſatisfaction and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not only of manie zelous and vertuous youngmen already aſſembled in Rome, to inioy the benefite of this College, hearing of his Holines intention before, but alſo of al other ſincere Catholique Englishmen, which ſought the good of their countrie, before their ovvne priuat. The firſt Rector of this College vvas father Robert Parſons of the ſame Societie, a man vvithout manie vvoordes, commended abundantly by his vvoorkes. And shortly againe in the yeare 1580. at the inſtance of M. D. Allen in the name of English Catholiques, father General of the ſame Societie, agreed alſo to ſend Engliſh Ieſuits into this harueſt, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent the ſame F. Parſons and father Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, both men of moſt excellent good ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents. And the next yeare very notable men alſo, F. Heyvvod and F. Holt, and ſo continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the like miſſions are maintained ſtil. Then the Seminaries and the Societie, with other Prieſts remaining of the old ſtore, labored iointly and merily together, for the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:150527:29"/> of our countrie <hi>vnamines in domo Dei.</hi> There were in England before this yeare, of the College of Dovvay, about ſeuentie Prieſts, (vvhich vvere not for euerie shire tvvo) and as yet none of the College of Rome. But this yeare 1580. entered the Realme, of both the Colleges, and of the Societie, and other Prieſts, that had liued before in Rome, and els vvhere priuatly, nere fourtie. And the next yeare aboue fourtie more. Which great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of vvorkemen, and eſpecially the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in of leſuites (Whom the Heretiques litle expected, and leſſe vvished) vvrought diuerſe effects. Some ſtormed, others ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired; ſome ſought to intrap them in ſnares; others to be inſtructed, and ſpiritually rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by them; ſome imagined to diſpatch al Ieſuites, and Seminarie Prieſts, out of the Realme againe, by publique Proclamations and more ſeuere parliament Satutes, and greater perſecution of al Catholiques. But no malice being able to ouerthrovv the vvork of God, ſtil Catholiques increaſed in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and in corage, and more vvere willing to ſuffer and to die for their faith, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; more and more vvere incenſed vvith deſire to go to the Seminaries; and ſome immediatly to the holie Societie, that ſo they might enter into the ſame vvorke, and be participant of the ſame glorious revvard. <hi>Of</hi> which ſorte ſome be already in heauen, others yet laboring in the vinyard. By occaſion
<pb facs="tcp:150527:29"/> of theſe nevv lavves, and of more preaching writing, and perſecution follovving, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie poore ſoules ſleeping in ſinne and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in diuerſe parts of the Realme, heard of theſe heroical attempts, of men that had dedicated and conſecrated their liues, to ſaue the ſoules of their deare contrimen. And that not only tvvo great Colleges of Englishmen did dayly ſend Prieſts amongſt them; but alſo the Societie of IESVS, which continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſendeth ſuch men into the furtheſt parts of the vvorld, to conuert Infidels, doth alſo ſend into England, to conuert their countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from Schiſme and Hereſie. Al theſe bruites did exceding much good, and much more the often preachings, ſvvete conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, moſt exemplar liefe, continual praiers, and daylie offering of the dreadful Sacrifice, made manie to open the dores of their ſoules, <hi>and out of manie harts cogitations were reueled</hi> And no meruel, that manie merueled to ſee and heare theſe things, for ſo it happeneth vvhenſoeuer ſuch men come into anie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie to preach Chriſt and the Catholique do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. As Sainct Auguſtin the Monk our Apoſtle, brought al England into admiration when he came vvith his felovves, and taught vs the vvav to ſaluation. Al the hil-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of Iurie merueled, hearing ſo admirable things, at the Natiuitie of S. Iohn Baptiſt <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the precurſor of Chriſt. And al England merueled vvhen they vnderſtood of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:150527:30"/> mens Apoſtolical comming to reſtore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> faith, which at the feaſt of the ſame S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Natiuitie, iuſt tvventie one yeares before, vvas abandoned. Manie vvith great furie and malice, ſpecially ſome Miniſters cried trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſedition, conſpiracie aganſt the Quene and the Realme. And albeit the vviſer ſorte knevv vvel ynough theſe men meant no trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ſaluation vnto al; yet treaſon it muſt be called for pollicies ſake, and crueltie muſt be vſed, to trie if they might ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this zeale; which they could no more do, then the Ievves could quench the zeale kindled firſt in the holie Apoſtles vpon whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday. For vvhy? Chriſt our Sauiour had ſaid before that time, which he performeth to the vvorlds end, that he <hi>came not to ſend peace</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (to vvit a blind peace in ſinne and error) <hi>but the ſvvorde, and ſeparation.</hi> I came to caſt fire on the earth; <hi>and what wil I elſe</hi> (ſaith our meeke Lord) <hi>but that it be kindled,</hi> and burne? The ſmoke of which fire ſo trubled the eyes of the Ievvish counſel, that it made Gamaliel geue no il aduiſe, to let the Apoſtles alone, and ſee vvhat iſſue their attempts vvould haue. Some of the Quenes counſel shevved them ſelues of the ſame opinion, in this caſe. iudging it vaine to kil Prieſts in England, ſo long as more come after them, from the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, and from a Religious Societie that dieth not. And amongſt others, one M. Fletvvood a
<pb facs="tcp:150527:30"/> Iuſtice of peace in his countrie, and a note proteſtant, when ſitting vppon cauſes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, he heard that there vvas one M. Lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rence Iohnſon a young man, and a Seminarie Prieſt (aftervvards a Martyr) commen into the ſame Prouince, <hi>Nay then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we ſtriue in vaine, we hoped theſe old Papistical Prieſts dying, al Papiſtrie should haue died, and ended with them; but this new broode wil neuer be rooted out, it is impoſsible euer to be rid of them, nor to extirpat this Papiſtical faith out of the land.</hi> And much more manie Heretiques deſpaired of euer effectuating this their deſire, to abolish the Catholique Religion in England; vvhen they ſavve this nevv fire of the Societie of IESVS ſeaze vpon English harts. Wherupon manie of al other ſorts of people, and ſome alſo of their Rabbins and greateſt Doctors diſvvaded, ſo much as they could, from rigorous perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Ieſuits, Seminarie Prieſts and of al other Catholiques; for that the more they should blovv this fire, the more it vvould burne. As namely Doctor Humfrey of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, did ſo much diſlike the putting to death of father Campion, that he could not diſſemble his counſel and opinion (no not after the Martyrs death, vvhen it vvas to late to recal him to liefe againe) but in his booke intituled: <hi>De praxi Romanae Curiae</hi> bevvai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ouerſight of thoſe that cauſed his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath; affirming that in Campion the prouerb,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:31"/> 
               <hi>Mortuus non mordet,</hi> vvas not true in Campian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Campianus enim mortuus adhuc mordet. For Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>being dead doth yet bite.</hi> Wherby, and by innumerable other exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and teſtimonies, al the vvorld doth ſee (though ſome of mere malice vvil not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it) that the Catholique cauſe is merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous vvel amended by the coming of zealous Seminarie Prieſts, and of Ieſuites. That by their abode the ſame good is dayly augmented and multiplied. And therfore the parting à vvay of either ſorte (which God forbid) muſt nedes be an intolerable loſſe, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion of our countrie, how ſoeuer ſome few catholiques, theſe later yeares falling into faction, wish al the Ieſuites and manie others to be remoued from this worke both within and without the Realme.</p>
            <p>But how much more neceſſarie it is, that theſe fevv diſturbers of the common good, be corrected, or remoued, shalbe eaſie to iudge if vve examine from vvhat roote, this ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of theirs procedeth, and vvhither it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. For euident it is, by this litle I haue novv ſaid, that ſometime al ranne vvel, al ſovved good ſeede, al labored in peace, vnion and mutual loue.</p>
            <p>Whence then came this il ſeede, this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, this diſſention, this debate, vvhich novv appeareth? <hi>The enimie man hath ſowed it,</hi> and it is a maſſin of manie vvedes. Old Satan ſeing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> infinite good fruit ſpring and proſper, in the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:31"/> fertil English filde, of mere enuie (for that is his propertie) ſo bevvitched ſome by am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, vaine liking of themſelues, and deſire to be eſtemed, and preferred before others; that ſeing other men do more good, haue more credite, and be more eſtemed then themſelues, begane to repine and diſdaine at others more eſtimation; and not being able othervviſe to excel, nor yet match them; fel into that bad ſinck of emulation, and anger againſt thoſe of better talents and vertues, that they could not abide to heare others more commended then them ſelues. As short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared by their ruſtie <hi>Raca,</hi> and mutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. For vvhen they chaunched to read, or heare other mens greater praiſes, ſtreight auerting their countenance, inſinuated as in clovvdes, or in general termes, as if they knevv theſe men not to be ſo good, nor ſo lerned, nor vviſe, as they vvere reputed; and ſo proceded from degree to degree into open detraction, falſe ſclandring, malicious accuſing, ſcandalous publishing, and into moſt abſurde and impudent auouching of faults, deuiſed by them ſelues, or wraſted from other mens fovvle mouthes, and made worſe and agrauated, againſt their brethren; for no other true cauſe, but for that they are eſtemed their betters, and to bring them ſelues therby to more equal balance, and ſo to be thought as good as they.</p>
            <p>To theſe vices, other the like did alſo
<pb facs="tcp:150527:32"/> concurre, as ſeruants and copemates, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtil made the perſons more and more diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and vnlike in qualities. VVherby alſo the emulation vvas more increaſed. As the more looſe and idle life of ſome, made them diſlike the better diſcipline and greater dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in others. Alſo haſtines of nature pronnes to anger, vvith litle mortificacion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inordinat paſſions, much impatience and the like il behauiour, made ſome Prieſts leſſe deſired of other Catholiques, and herevpon again did often grovv falſe ſuſpicions, ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſurmiſſes, and rash iudgments, that they were caſt out of fauoure, or diſgraced by thoſe vvhom they did emulate. Where as indeede there vvas no other cauſe, but their ovvne il cariage, and eſpecialy their il ton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gues againſt good and innocent perſons vvhom for their more credite, they coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not brooke. Vpon theſe ſtrings, and the lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſubtile ſerpent plaid his part, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diligence of Heretiques toke hold of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to nourish and egge forvvard theſe humurous phantaſies, and animoſities of buſie heads, fraight vvith ambition, and deſire to rule others, vvho haue neither vvel lerned to rule themſelues, nor to be ruled; being voide of that charitie, by vvhich they ought to build, to the increaſe of the vvhole bodie, and not to diminish the ſame bodie, nor to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor pul dovvne that which others build.
<pb facs="tcp:150527:32"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd al this principally becauſe they ſavve our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate good Cardinal in his time, and others with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, eſpecially the Ieſuits, both then and after, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be more in credite and fauour vvith great Princes, and other great or rich perſons: which they often obiect for a great quarrelle; not mentioning that they ate more eſtemed vvith the meaner and poorer forte alſo. But I pray you (deare brethren and freinds) that vvould be more eſtemed then you are, tel me vvhat fault is in the fathers, or in other men for this? Is not honour and eſtimation the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard of vertue? eſpecially amongſt good men: ſuch as you can not denie theſe Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques to be, vvho ordinarily prefer Ieſuits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you? vvil you blame them for being more vertuous, and for deſeruing better then you? for if they did not deſerue better, ſo manie good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen vvould not more eſteme them. Or els vvil you blame the vvhole Catholique vvorld and al other countries, that beginne, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to be Catholiques, for embracing the Ieſuits labours more then yours? vvil you barre mens iudgments in making their ovvne choice, by vvhat ſpiritual men they vvil be chiefly directed? Or vvil you abridge their liberties, and force them to leaue the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, vvhoſe conuerſation, and diſcretion they like better then yours; and to be directed by you, of vvhom they haue not ſo great an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? Is this the libertie you talke of, and which
<pb facs="tcp:150527:33"/> you promiſe, if you may haue your will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ghoſtly children shal firſt forſake their gloſtly fathers whom they moſt deſire, and then be bond to thoſe which you like beſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Truly moſt men thinke, that nevv ones of your appointment, vvil not be ſo good. You vvil ſay, they shal be better and fitter. you can ſay no leſſe. for vvhy should they change but for the better? And yet we tel yoy ſtil, that moſt men think, they vvil not be ſo good. You ſay there is no iuſt, nor reaſonable cauſe, VVhy Catholiques should entertaine Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites before you, folovv their counſels ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then yours, aduenture al they haue by receuing them, then by receuing you, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to their diſcretions, the diſtribution of their almoſe and charitable beneuolence<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more then to yours. Theſe be the blocks y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtumble at. And you can no more condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Ieſuites, for condeſcending to ſerue good Catholiques in theſe and the like things, then you condemne your ſelues for al that you do to the liking of your ghoſtlie children.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you vvould haue them, vvhen they are vvilled to do ſuch good offices, to refuſe to do them, and to ſend them to you; as though al ſuch affayres depended vpon your vvills, vvho should manage them; and as though the requeſt of the partie, vvere not ſufficient vvarrant, for euerie one, to do the good he can, in order and ſubordination to his Superior. Yet ſuppoſe the fathers should
<pb facs="tcp:150527:33"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rect ſuch perſons to you, as come to them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inke you that the parties vvould forthvvith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>paire to you? intertayne you? folovv your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ounſel? commit much to your diſcretions? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſurely, in this they vvould not folovv the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athers counſel: For thoſe that ſeke firſt and principally, to direct their liues and actions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y aduiſe of the Fathers of the Societie, do ſecondly deſire to be directed by ſuch other Prieſts, as moſt imitate the Fathers in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of liefe, ſuch as loue them beſt, and beſt agree vvith them. And the cauſe of this better liking, which ſo manie haue to be aſſiſted by Ieſuites (beſides the particular ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of euerie one) muſt nedes be ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant good and conſpicuous things, in the Order it ſelf, which are not in our vocation. As particularly, their Religious profeſſion, their ſtricter diſcipline and ſet rules of life, their renounciation to al dignities, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties in this vvorld, and the reſignation of their ovvne wills, liuing alvvayes in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to a Superiour; vvho taketh due account of their behauiors, of their labours of their fruites, and of their talents, what they are able to do, where and wherin they may do moſt good, and ſo the ſame Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior imploieth them. If they haue imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they haue ſpecial approued remedies to amend the ſame: and if they correct not themſelues the ſooner; this Superior in the meane time hath care to cure euerie one, and
<pb facs="tcp:150527:34"/> is readie to anſvver for his ſubiec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, vvherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he abides, which is a good vvarrant; for their hoſt, and vvhoſoeuer dealeth vvith them. And ſpecial care is alwayes taken, to haue them very fit for miſſion, before they be ſent, and at al ſeaſons they are readie to be changed from their imployments. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoueuer they go, they are ſtil in a ſtrong caſtle, defended with ioined forces of expert ſoldiars, firme vvals, good armour, and al neceſſarie furniture; which make not only themſelues more ſafe, from the aſſaults of the ſpiritual enemie, but alſo by hovv much they are better guarded and furnished, ſo much more able are they, to aſſiſt, guide, and lead others ſafly. Whereas vve of the other vocation (though Eccleſiaſtical and Clergimen) are abrode in the vvorld, hold our intereſts, proprieties or poſſibilities, in the vvorld. vve are more at our ovvne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and make not ſo often account of our baylivvickes, nor yeld ſo frequent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conings, vvhat profite vve make of our ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, nor vvhat fruit anie reape by our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; vve vvander abrode as ſingle men in open filds, or vnfenſed villages, ſo much more ſubiect to tentations, as vve are more intangled in the vvorld, and the leſſe able to reſiſt, becauſe vve haue not renounced the vvorld, nor our ovvne vvils. And vvhy should vve then meruel, that men are more afeard to be guided by vs, then by thoſe they finde
<pb facs="tcp:150527:34"/> more like to guide them aright. And what wrong is donne to vs, by other mens ſeeking ther ovvne ſecucicie? Thus vve ſee briefly vvhence this controuerſie ſprong, and hovv this il ſeede came into our fild, vvhere firſt none but good vvas ſovven.</p>
            <p>Now vve are to conſider vvherin it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth. Which is not (as our aduerſaries vvould haue it, and falſly reporte) in anie point or article of the Catholique faith; for vvhoſoeuer obſtinately defendeth anie ſuch error is an Heretike and no Catholique; but it conſiſteth in the varietie of opinions, deſires and endeuors, about the perſons, that are ſpecially to direct others as guides or heades, and about the maner of proceeding in our common vvorke, for the reducing of our countrie to the Catholique Religion. And thus farre vve al agree, that ſome fevv, or rather ſome one, ought to be chiefe leader of al the reſt, becauſe manie heades hauing or arrogating equal autoritie, muſt nedes make confuſion. And at the begining, al that entred into this holie vvorke either gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vvholy to the direction of D. Allen (and that long before he vvas Cardinal) or els concurred vvith him, in al their actions ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this purpoſe. not anie one Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que man of our nation oppoſing againſt him, from the time of erecting of Dovvay College til that about the yeare 82. three or foure gentlemen in Paris began the firſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction
<pb facs="tcp:150527:35"/> againſt the ſaid D. Allen and againſt F. Parſons. Sir Frances Inglefild. M. Hugh Ovven, and al other agreing vvith them. For theſe men neither vouchſafing to folovv the high and ſtraight vvay, alredy vvel found out and very vvel proceded in, nor to ſit quiet and at reſt, deuiſed other byvvaies, caſt nevv plots, which neuer had good effect, but much hindred and ouerthrevv diuerſe good things intended, as is vvel knovvne. They thought it reaſon to exclude D. Allen, by the title of <hi>a Breuiarie man,</hi> from dealing any further in helping of our countrie, but only by his education of ſchollers to be Prieſts. For theſe men vvould geue them inſtructions, hovv to behaue themſelues tovvards the ſtate of England. And ſo they vvould bring D. Allen and al his, into their countrie: as one of them was not ashamed to bragge and that in D. Allens ovvne preſence.</p>
            <p>In like ſorte they excluded F. Parſons, from their counſel, and from knovvledge of their deuiſes, becauſe he is a religious man: as though he vvere not more fit, and no vvay leſſe fit for that. For vvho is ſo meete to geue aduiſe, in ſpiritual or in vvorldlie affaires as thoſe which haue renounced al priuat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and proprietie in the vvorld? Doth not our Sauiour ſay, that thoſe which haue left <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> al in this vvorld, <hi>shal ſit with him in iudgement, and iudge the world?</hi> Doth not S. Paule hervpon inferr, that ſeing he and other Apoſtles, and
<pb facs="tcp:150527:35"/> Religious men <hi>shal iudge the world, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtata</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Angels; much more it is conuenient, that they shal iudge ſecular affaires?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They excluded Sir Frances Inglefild, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had bene long forth of the Realme, and novv ignorant (as they ſuppoſed) of the ſtate of things there; as though he that had bene of the priuie Councel to Q Marie, vvere not more able both for his vviſdome, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, and long experience, to be a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, then anie of them? or that he had not as particular knovvledge, as anie of them, hovv things ſtood in England? They exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded M. Hugh Ovven, M. Thomas Fitzherbert, and aftervvards ſir Charles Arundel, and al others, that agreed vvith. D. Allen, becauſe they vvould not leaue him, and the vvhole nation, and hang vpon them. For the ſame cauſe they could not abide ſir William Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, finding him to agree ſo wel with D. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, ſir Frances, F. Parſons, F. Holt, M. Ovven, and others; and alſo becauſe he is a ſoldiar, and they better ſtatesmen, in their ovvne conceipts; as though he being ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novvmed a ſoldiar, vvere therfore leſſe fit, to geue his aduiſe hovv our countrie may be brought againe to the Catholique faith, being othervviſe a man of as ſound iudgment, as any of them, and (as al that knovv him and them can vvitnes) as farre more ſincere, more vertuous, more ſtudious, more labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to help his countrie, and al his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie
<pb facs="tcp:150527:36"/> men, as he is more valient in the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> then they are, which is no ſmale difference.</p>
            <p>They admitted the Earle of Weſtmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to their Partie, ſo farre only as he vvould concurre vvith them, to oppoſe againſt, and to ouerthwart other mens good labours: but by no meanes vvould they take him for their chiefe. Thomas Morgan vvas the beginner of al; wherof it is called <hi>Morgans faction.</hi> but M. Charles Paget vvas chiefe commander: the Lord Paget vvas content to be ruled by them. wherupon they complained the more, that the Earle of vveſtmerland vvould not be ruled alſo; thus this contradiction began. And vpon this ground they haue continued the ſame, entertaining and imploying al mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents they could get, to yeald to their bend. So far forth that vvithin tvvo or three yeares, they ſeduced tvvo Seminarie Prieſts to treate vvith them, and to be imployed by them, yea one of them at leaſt to treate vvith Secretarie Walſingham. And aftervvardes induced the ſame tvvo, to write tvvo bookes the one againſt F. Parſons and al Ieſuits; the other againſt the Cardinal. Eſpecially againſt his Epiſtle vvritten in iuſtification of Sir William Stanley his rendring the Citie of Dauenter to the right Lord therof, the king Catholique. Which fact vvas not only iuſt, lavvful, and neceſſarie by the lavves of God and Nations, in reſpect both of the place, and of himſelf; but alſo he had a
<pb facs="tcp:150527:36"/> particular licence for his perſon, of the Earle of Leceſter to depart from that ſeruice, and to repaire vvhere he vvould, for his better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. which licence hath bene ſeene by ſome English Proteſtants: Agents ſometimes in Flanders, and is to be shevved vvhenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer occaſion shal require. As yet this faction vvas but ſmale and greene amongſt Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques in England; for the tvvo foreſaid Prieſts very shortly retired thence, and verie fevv durſt breake openly vvith their brethren, nor with the Fathers, ſo long as the Cardinal liued. But preſently vpon his death, ſome other vnquiet ſpirits, though priſoners for their faith (hauing long exerciſed their good felovv priſoners with much patience) more openly ioyned themſelues vvith the ſame trubleſome, with whom they had ſecretly dealt before. And ſo did alſo manie of the ſcholars in Rome, againſt the Protector himſelfe, and their other Superiors. Sodeinly becomming great ſtates men, as then they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. For the better appeaſing of which diſſentions, and preuenting the like, al Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques generally deſired to haue ſome Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, and Subordination in the English Clergie.</p>
            <p>But for ſo much as al former Subordination vvas vvholy interrupted vvithin the Realme, it could not otherwiſe be reſtored but by the Sea Apoſtolique, or by ſpecial commiſſion geuen by his Holines for this purpoſe. For novv in
<pb facs="tcp:150527:37"/> our countrie vve had neither Primat; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other Bishop, nor Ordinarie of anie one Dioceſe; nor anie Archprieſt; nor Vicarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; nor Archdeacon; nor Deane of anie Chapiter; nor anie Chapiter; nor other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical communitie at al; nor ſo much as an ordinarie Paſtor, nor Vicar of anie parish; but only priuat Prieſts, vvho had ſubdelegat faculties in court of conſcience only, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Sacraments, and ſome other ſpiritual functions.</p>
            <p>But theſe were no more a myſtical bodie, then certaine prouiſion of ſtone, lime, and timber, are a houſe or a church, before they be compact together, and formed vvith vval<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and roofe: for euen ſo vve were a certaine prouiſion of Prieſts ordained, for reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our decaied Hierarchie, but vvere not diſpoſed of in anie ſubordination vnder a head. And ſo had no poſſible meanes in our ovvne nation, to make anie Prouincial Concel Synode, Conuocation, or Chapiter, nor had anie electiue, or deciſiue voices or ſuffrages, to chooſe ſupperior or other officer, nor to determine anie thing iuridically. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the due ioyning of Clergie men to make a Hierarchie (none of them hauing further autoritie) diuerſe of the chiefeſt and eldeſt ſort aſvvel in England, as in banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment humbly propoſed this our caſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to his Holines, vvith ſuch ſuggeſtions as to them ſemed moſt mete. Manie thought
<pb facs="tcp:150527:37"/> it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crated, for the better gouernment of our Church, and moſt ſpecially for adminiſtring the holie Sacrament of Confirmation; though our Cardinal in his time, vvas not of that minde; for if he had, it had bene done. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, after mature conſultation, his Holines reſolued to make an Archprieſt vvith tvvelue Aſſiſtants, to gouerne the reſt in England. And vpon the particular information of the ſame chiefe and eldeſt ſorte of English prieſts teſtifying the ſingular good talents, vertue, learning, vviſdome, zeale, diſcretion, and other good parts, and conſiderable circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, concurring praeeminently in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of M. George Blackvvel, this autoritie of Archprieſt vvas laid vpon him; to the great ioye and ſingular liking of al, except a very fevv, eſpecially thoſe that aſpired to haue bene promoted themſelues. Who hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by our Protectors letters, that this Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt vvas conſtituted, and tvvelue Aſſiſtants appointed, deferred to ſubmit themſelues, til they might ſee further confirmation therof from his Holines. And shortly they ſent tvvo meſſengers to Rome, not ſo much to learne his Holines true meaning and intention (for they knevv it already, but thought they vvere not bound to acknovvledge it) as to trie, if they could procure this autoritie to be recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or altered; and ſpecially to be remoued to ſome other perſon; alleaging againſt their
<pb facs="tcp:150527:38"/> appointed Superiour, nothing but meere fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>hoods, and that he agreeth too vvel vvith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſuits, and ſpecially vvith F. Parſons.</p>
            <p>So the controuerſie is novv come to this ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial point; whether the R. R. Archprieſt be a ſufficient and fit man for the place he is in, ſeing he agreeth vvel vvith the Ieſuits, and namely vvith F. Parſons; and concurreth vvith them to gaine ſoules; or that he shoud be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, and ſome other put in his, or in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me higher place, that diſliketh of F. Parſons, and other Ieſuites; and that the Ieſuites should alſo depart out of England, and be remoued from the gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of al English Seminaries, euen from thoſe which they haue procured? Al vvhich is ſo abſurd and barbarous an attempt that it needeth no further confutation. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie childe, and ſimple man or vvoman doth knovv, that it is a good thing to build a Church or a College, and to gaine ſoules: and that pulling dovvne, and hindring of ſuch vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes is very naught and wicked. Againe, it is a moſt knowen thing (and none of the malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenrs can poſſibly denie it) that F. Parſons, for his part, hath moſt painfully and frutfully la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to helpe his countrie aboue tvventie tvvo yeares already, that is, ſince the English College in Rome vvas founded. In procuring vvherof his part was not leaſt, vvith D. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and D. Levvis, agreing in his intention with vvhoſoeuer vvas moſt ſincere.</p>
            <p>In England he did more good in tvvo
<pb facs="tcp:150527:38"/> yeares, then I thinke anie of his emulators haue donne in tvventie; or are like to doe in al their life. For one example; let his lerned and vertous bookes teſtifie written againſt <hi>Hanmer</hi> and <hi>Charck,</hi> and in <hi>detection</hi> of <hi>Iohn Nicols;</hi> and <hi>the reaſons,</hi> vhy Catholiques refuſe to goe to the Proteſtants Church. And eſpecially the <hi>Chriſtian Directorie,</hi> firſt ſet forth vvith the title, of <hi>Reſolution,</hi> ſo often printed ſince, and ſtil deſired. A vvorke worthie to be in al languages, and in al mens hands. By which innumerable Catholiques, haue ben, and daily are much confirmed, conforted, and edified; Schiſmatikes and Heretikes continually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted; as very manie doe daily reporte of themſelues, that they vvere conuerted by reading F. Parſons booke of Reſolution. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his going out of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which vvas dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les (as manie good effects haue shevved) by Gods ſpecial prouidence (as vvas D. Allens going thence alſo, vvhen he had donne much good) he firſt got tvvo thousa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ducats of gold (which do make ſix hundreth pounds ſtarling) euerie yeare to Dovvay College, then reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Rhemes. He procured alſo a College for English children in Evv. Aftervvards tvvo more notable Colleges for English ſcholars, and tvvo other reſidences for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Prieſts in Spain. An other College like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe in Flanders, vvhen by reaſon of the vvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in France, that of Evv ceaſed. And (which may haue place vvith the greateſt and moſt
<pb facs="tcp:150527:39"/> difficult vvorke or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> College of Rome, to a mirrour or ſpectacle of right Collegial peace, mutual loue, great vertue, and of much increaſe in learning, which a few yeares agoe, vvas fallen into extreme danger of vtter ruine, by diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the members, and tumultous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of ſuperiors and good orders. I omit here his redeming of manie English capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from fire, gallovves, and gallies, vvith his charitie in procuring them reliefe, and manie of them ſufficient meanes to liue; and manie other good deedes, both in general to his vvhole nation, and to innumerable particular perſons. By this that is already ſaid, euerie one may ſufficiently ſee, vvhether it be good, that the chiefe of our Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchie in England, and his freinds and ſubiects should agree vvith this father, and al the Societie; or that they should picke quarels, and make vvarrs againſt them, contemne and abandon al the good vve haue, and may haue by them. Which in dede vvere to hinder the beſt meanes of increaſing the Catholique faith in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and conſequently to hold hereſie there the longer; an ſo I end this point, and come to the laſt.</p>
            <p>In vvich I am to declare, betvven vvhom this controuerſie remaineth. And this alſo is partly donne alreadie. For ſeing the ſpecial drift of this contention is, to haue the Archprieſt remoued from his office, and the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:39"/> Ieſuits out of England, and from al Engli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Seminaries; it is euident that the controuerſie is betvven the Archprieſt, vvith al aſvvel Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits as other Prieſts, and Catholiques, that alovve or like of the Eccleſiaſtical ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lately reſtored in England; and the mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents vvith their partners, that oppugne or diſlike the ſame: and not betwen the Ieſuits, and the Seminarie Prieſts. vvhich can in no other ſence be iuſtified, then one may ſay <hi>an Egyptian is white,</hi> becauſe his teeth are vvhite. At leaſt, it is as falſe as vvas the report made to king Dauid, that <hi>al his ſonnes were ſlaine:</hi> vvhen only Amnon vvas ſlaine, and no more. As I <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 13.</note> vvil novv further demonſtrate, that the truth may appeare, and the Seminarie Prieſts (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king abſolutly of the chiefeſt beſt and farre greateſt part) from the begining of the firſt Seminarie to this day, may be clered from this iniurious ſclander.</p>
            <p>Firſt therfore when D. Allen began this holie vvorke, he had a chiefe care to haue his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege vvhere ther vvas alſo a College of Ieſuits that therby he might the better haue their continual conſel and help, ſpiritualy and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally in al his affaires. And namely that the ſtudents might frequent the holie Sacraments and ſome leſſons in the fathers College. which they did continually, til both they and the Ieſuits were driuen from Doway by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of heretiques, for their more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous profeſſion of the Catholique Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:40"/> then the vulgar ſorte of Catholiques com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly shevv. Which wel shevveth the good agreement, betvven the Ieſuits and the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie at that time. The ſame is alſo manifeſt by that D. Allen in his returne from Rome, before he had yet begunne his College, ſo gladly ioyned himſelf in companie, vvith F. Maximilian de Capella of the ſame Societie, Doctor and Reader of Diuinitie in their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege in Dovvay: whoſe good aduiſes, and ſpecial commendations to diuerſe charitable men much furthered the ſame good beginings.</p>
            <p>Aftervvards F. Antonius Poſſiuinus, and F. Oliuerius Manereus moſt affectionatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring vvith their informations to their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and he and they commending the ſtate of the English College to Pope Gergorie the thirtenth, obtained his monethly penſion for them. After this againe, the Catholique kings penſion (which is greater then the Popes) vvas not only procured, by F. Parſons commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and trauel (as is noted before) but alſo by his induſtrie moſt eſpecially, or by F. Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, or ſome other of the fathers, it is ſtil payd. which vvith manie other notorious examples of greate benefits, which D. Allen, and his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie haue receiued of the Fathers, do vvel declare the mutual liking, ſincere loue, intire affection, and confident dealing betvven him and the Societie, and betvven al his and al their true folovvers and freinds.</p>
            <p>The ſame is vvel teſtified alſo on the Cardinal
<pb facs="tcp:150527:40"/> his part. for though he vvas not able to requite them in other good turnes, yet he euer grat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowleged the great good our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie reapeth by the holie Societie; as is to be ſeene in moſt of his printed bookes. ſpecially in his <hi>Apologie of twelue Martyrs;</hi> in his <hi>Anſwer to the pretenſed Iuſtice of England;</hi> and moſt particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his <hi>Apologie,</hi> written by him iointly in defence of the charitable indeuors <hi>of the Societie, and of the Seminaries.</hi> In which elegant booke, next to the worthines of Gods cauſe, he moſt amply commendeth good Pope Gregorie the thirtenth, and the holie Societie of IESVS. Moreouer touching his moſt gratful affection towards F. Parſons, omitting other innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable proofes, his letters written shortly after he was made Cardinal, to M. Thomas Bailey<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his ſubſtitute in the College at Rhemes, do ſufficiently teſtifie in theſe words; <hi>you are al glad and reioyce</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for my promotion. God graunt it be, as</hi> I <hi>truſt it is, to his more honour, and good of our Countrie, for elſe</hi> I <hi>had rather haue kept my black cappe ſtil. But how much ſoeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r you haue cauſe to reioyce in this behalf, ſo much more, al you, that loue me ſo dearly, are bound by a new obligation, to loue, and be gratful to the whole Societie, and namely to our own ſpecial good Father, and chiefe cooperator. For next vnder Heauen F. Parſons made me Cardinal.</hi> And more to the ſame effect in the ſame letter.</p>
            <p>And that he continued the ſame affection, and ſincere correſpondence with the fathers, his owne good Nephew M. Thomas Allen,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:41"/> and ſundrie of his letters doe teſtifie. amongſt which one vvas vvritten not long before his death, to one that then began to be malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> and ſince hath ioyned vvith others. yea and (as is more then probable) dravvne others vvith him. This then being clere tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Cardinal, the ſame muſt alſo needs be true, in al that ſincerly loued, and agreed vvith him. For othervviſe in breaking his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commandement, in that verie point, vvherin they pretend to agree vvith him, they erre as farre from the truth, as <hi>he that ſaith he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>loueth God and breaketh his commandements.</hi> In ſo much that during the Cardinals time, not aboue foure or fiue in England, beſides flat Apoſtates, durſt shevv the contrarie; though after his death more appeared: therby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvraing their former diſſimulations, their litle regard of his ſvvete, and fatherly admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and their meruelous ingratitude both tovvards him their late Superior, and the fathers, by vvhom they had receaued no ſmal benefite in their education and learning.</p>
            <p>But God be thanked, yet al theſe are not nor euer vvere ſo manie, neither in England nor abroad, as they vſe to count themſelues. For vpon occaſion of their accuſing the fathers ſome yeares agoe, in the name of our nation, trial vvas made amogſt the English in the lovv countries by manie ſeueral letters, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions to a general atteſtation, remaning in record to be ſene; vvhere ſo manie of the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:41"/> eldeſt and chiefeſt clergie men of our nation, and ſome chiefe of the laitie alſo, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie others of good account, teſtified the great and charitable offices of the fathers tovvards our contrie, that of three or foure hundred, ſcarſe foureteene refuſed to ſubſcribe. Of which ſome vvere oppoſites to the fathers, and ſome neutrals. And in England ſcarſe tenne, at that time, did shevv themſelues againſt the fathers.</p>
            <p>Againe at this day, though there be ſome more Seminarie Prieſts latly ſeduced, by the ouer diligence of the former ringleaders, yet they are ſtil matched, and ouer matched in number, vvith thoſe only that be in office, and autoritie for the ſeruice of our countrie; vvho for that they are officers ought and muſt by al reaſon, preuaile againſt priuat men, if they vvere manie more, as in dede they are rather fevver. But if vve doe alſo compare (as vvhy shal vve not?) the vvhole number aſvvel of the ancient Catholique, as later Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie Prieſts, which reuerence, loue, and like vvel both the fathers and the Archprieſt, and al other ſuperiours in our English clergie, they vvil be founde tvventie, or thirtie ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſo manie, as the part or particle that oppoſeth againſt the ſame Fathers, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, and the reſt of the bodie. And if vve extend this compariſon, to al Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie men deſigned for the ſame vvorke, or yet goe forvvard to al English Catholiques,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:42"/> or finally obſerue the iudgments of al Catho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ques in the world, the further we procede, the more oddes we finde. nature and reaſon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing al men of conſideration, as wel to like and loue ſo holie, and ſo perfect an Order of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious men, and to alowe and approue what ſo euer ſuch a vvhole Order alloweth and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth: as alſo to prefer the ordinances and procedings of lawful Superiors, before the diſliking of others, that complaine or ſpeake il therof. And thus much may ſuffice for decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that this controuerſie riſen amongſt. English Catholiques, is not in matter of faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or betwen the Seminarie Prieſts and the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, as is vniuſtly ſaid, but about the Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination lately reſtored in our clergie; and the fathers of the Societie labouring in the ſame worke, and ſo is betwen the bodie of English Catholiques, that is al the heads with moſt of the members, agreing wholy with the fathers; and a ſmal partie of oppoſits diſliking the ſame Subordination, and the fathers of the Societie.</p>
            <p>To returne therfore whence I am digreſſed, I moſt hartely wish, and in our L. I. Ch. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantlie beſech al our diſcontented brethren, to liue and dye in peace, and perfect vnion, ſo much as in vs lieth, with al the world, but more eſpecially with al Catholiques, and moſt of al with our Superiors, brethren, and felow ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diars. as this our bleſſed brother M. Wharton now a martyr, moſt gladly and louingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged his appointed Superiour, the R.
<pb facs="tcp:150527:42"/> R. Archprieſt; and moſt ſincerely alwayes agreed with the reuerend fathers of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of Ieſus. And yet was he as ancient, as graue, and as learned a Graduate of the Vniuerſitie of Oxford, as whoſoeuer of the diſcontented moſt vrgeth theſe reſpects. For he was felovv and companion in Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie College vvith the ſame M. George Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel novv Archprieſt, vvith M. Thomas Ford and M. Edward Burden both martyrs, and with M. William Sutton, after of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie: neither did he diſdaine that his equals, yea diuerſe otherwiſe his inferios, in degre, yeares, and lerning, were put in office, himſelfe remaining in his priuat ſtate. As vvere ſundrie of the tvvelue Aſſiſtants. Whom he alſo obeyed, and for his humiltie feruent charitie, and other great vertues, is now exalted to a glorious croune of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome. Which together vvith his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode and holie profeſſion, the ſame F. Sutton (by way of probable coniecture) congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated vvith him long before, in a letter da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Muſſipont the 17. of Nouember. 1584. which yet remaineth in the English College in Dovvay; by the ſame prouidence of God (as I may interpret) by which it was vvritten. The copie wherof I haue here adioined as it is in latin, ſuppoſing manie vvil deſire to reade it. Surely it is à letter vvorthie of a Ieſuit to a Seminarie Prieſt. The Superſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption only is in English, and is thus.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:43"/>
            <head>TO M. CHRISTOPHER WHARTON IN THE ENGLISH COLLEGE AT RHEMES.</head>
            <p>MAgnum mihi attulerunt ſolatium <hi>(opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Chriſtophore)</hi> tuae literae, quibus intellexi te non ſolum deſerta Anglicana noſtra Aegypto, à qua iam pridem pedem ſubtraxiſti, Eccleſiae matris obſequentiſsimum eſſe filium, ac iam illius foeliciſsimi Collegij alumnum; verum etiam ad ſacros Ordines, hoc eſt (vt nunc rem interpretor) ad ipſa martyrij auſpicia aſpiraſſe. Foelicem ego illum eſſe praedico, qui nunc in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia exiſtens, ſacro Reconciliationis faedere, ſe Deo, ac S. matri Eccleſiae aſtringit; Foelicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem verò qui maiori perfectionis deſiderio inar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcens, ad fontem illum (quem in hoc Martyrum Seminario Deus mihi aperuiſſe viſus eſt) accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vt maiori poſteà cum fiducia animi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudine certamen pro fide ineat. Foeliciſsimum denique qui ſacratiſsimis conſecrandi Dominici Corpor is myſterijs initiatus, ſuum iam quaſi ſanguinem, pro eiuſdem pientiſsimi Domini hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, eiuſque corpore myſtico conſecraſſe videtur. Hos tu ſiue foelicitatis, ſiue perfectionis gradus partim attigiſſe videris, partim praeſentis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi praeparatione conſcendere conaris. Quamuis
<pb facs="tcp:150527:43"/> enim non omnibus martyrij corona, etiam cum hoc cupiant, conceditur; ingentis tamen meriti eſt illa glorioſa ſanctae fidei confeſsio, quam tu tui<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortes quotidiè facitis, hoc praeſertim tam infoelici noſtrae infaeliciſsimae Angliae ſtatu ac tempore. Vbi tanta Sanctorum Myſteriorum conculcatio; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus diuini honoris contemptus; tamque horrenda rerum ſacrarum, ac perſonarum prophanatio &amp; deſpectus; vt iam verè fidelis ſit ſeruus, ac dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus Domini Saluatoris, eiuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> immaculatae ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae Eccleſiae Filius, qui ſe contra iſtas ruinas vt murum opponere, qui Sancta, Sancta, inclamare ac verè Sancta ea<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> auguſtiſsima Myſteria, caeleſtia<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſanctitatum iura, ab atrociſsimis hiſce contumelijs vindicare contendit. Et hic quidem eſt tuus ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, haec conditio, hic ordo ſacer. Nunquam mihi tam coniunctus fuiſti, quanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; domeſtica, illius Collegij in quo olim vnà <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iximus, &amp; peculiari ami<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> citia, olim chariſsimus, quam nunc es ſub vexillo Crucis, huiuſque ſanctae militiae communione.</p>
            <p>At enim quid nos miſeri vermiculi humi repentes, quibus tanta munia, tamque excelſa concredita ſunt? Nunquid tam eminentis digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis altiſsima myſteria, vel ſemel à lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge aſpicere, nedum attrectare, nedum conſecrare digni ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? Nunquid coeleſtis Ianuae claues geſtare, ac animabus praetioſo coeleſtis Agni ſanguine redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptis,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:44"/> Paradiſi aditum reſerare digni? Verè qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in tremendis hiſce officijs verſantur, identidem ſe animumque totum ac ſpiritum recolligere habent, oculoſque interiores ab exteriori rerum ſtrepitu, viſibilique ſpecie ſubtractos in diuiniora defigere, ibi ſe coram infinita &amp; ſuperbenedicta Dei Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtate proſternere, ac paululum animo reuoluere, quanta cum eius dignatione, fauore, &amp; gratia, iam coram illa immenſa Diuinitate, quam tremunt Angeli, eiuſque Throno, ac menſa regali, verſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur is, qui ſuo demerito, propter illius ſummo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nori irrogatam iniuriam, iam diu vt hoſtis &amp; extorris in tenebras exteriores amandandus fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, nihil<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> adhuc egit, quod ad tantas tam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> inueteratas contract as maculas eluendas ſatis eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. Tum in profundiſsimam quandam humilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem coram Deo ſuo deſcendere, imò in abyſſum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuae miſeriae, abiectionis, indignitatis &amp; nihilei tatis ſe abſcondere, ac ſacratiſsimis Chriſti vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus lauandum ſe humillime prebere, petere ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs ac gemitibus puritatem cordis, diuinam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiam, gratias ac virtutes, vt in domo Dei ſui coram ſanctiſsimo eius Throno, coram oculis tantae Maieſtatis, &amp; ſplendoris, inſpectante illo beatiſsimo ac lucidiſsimo ſanctorum choro, in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcepto munere dignè, vel ſaltem non indignè, &amp; ſine offenſa verſari queat. Sed quid ego haec,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:44"/> aliaúe tibi propino, qui iam ad fontem ſedes, vnde vberrimé diuinae diſciplinae fluenta iam diu in multos redundarunt? Hoc mihi concedet ſpero tua humanit as, vt dum te pro veteri noſtrae amicitia affari, adeo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſalutare libuit, interim me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum his verbis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monerem. Quaeſo mi reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ac dilecte domine Chriſtophore, vt in tuis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis ſacrificijs met memoriam facere velis, me<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquarum tuarum deuotionum participem efficias. Saluta precor meo nomine D. Edouardu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Burdenu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſi quis ſit alius Collegij S. Trinitatis: Item D. Edmundum Leukenorum, &amp; Arthurum Strat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordum, alioſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> noſtros familiares &amp; in Chriſto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectos. Vale. Muſsiponti. 17. Nouemb. 1584.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Veſtri ſemper amantiſsimus GVILIELMVS SVTTONVS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>Elſe vvhere this Epiſtle may be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into English. For novv after this long digreſſion, I make haſt to recite briefly, the other Martyrs of this holie yeare.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:45"/>
            <p> IN <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ovving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> happened, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> being made in the Countie and Citie of Lincolne, for certaine malefactors, that had committed a robberie; there vvere found in a common Inne, at the ſigne of the Sarazens head, tvvo ſtrangers cloſe in their chamber (vvho vvere in dede Prieſts, their names M. Thomas Sprot, and M. Thomas Hunt) vvhom the ſearchers vehemently ſuſpecting to be the men they ſought for, arreſted them vpon ſuſpition of felonie, examined them ſtraightly and ſeuerally, vvhat vvere their names, vvhere they vvere borne, vvhat condition or trade of life they vvere of, vvhen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce they came, vvhither they vvent, and what buſines they had there, vvhom they knevv in the Citie or therabout: ſo preſſing them, that to clere themſelues of the falſe ſuſpition of robberie, they confeſſed, that they vvere Catholiques, fled thither in hope to liue there more quietly, as ſtrangers for a time, then they could do where they vvere more knovvne. The ſame officers ſearching their males, found therin holie Oyle, and tvvo Breuiaries, which gaue ſuſpition that they vvere Prieſts. VVhervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they vvere brought to the Maior, and by him examined vpon theſe foure Articles. Firſt, vvhether they had bene at the Church vvithin theſe tenne, or tvvelue yeares? 2. If the Pope should inuade the Realme, vvhether they vvould take part with him, or vvith the Queene?
<pb facs="tcp:150527:45"/> 3. Whether they did take the Quene to be Supreme gouerneſſe of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland? 4. Whether they vvere Prieſts, or no?</p>
            <p>To theſe Interrogatories they anſvvered briefly, and conformably ech to other, vvith litle difference of vvordes, to this effect.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, that they vvere brought vp from their infancie, in the Catholique faith, and vvere neuer at the Proteſtants Church. To the ſecond, that when ſuch a caſe shal happen, which is not likelie, they wil an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver it. To the third, that the Pope is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme head of the Catholi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Church, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the vvorld. To the fourth they anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as before, that they vvere Catholiques: and further they thought themſelues not bound to anſvvere. For as al Chriſtians are bound to be Catholiques: ſo al are bound to confeſſe the ſame Catholique faith. But no man being bound to be a Prieſt, neither is he bound to confeſſe, vvhether he be a Prieſt or no. Neuer the leſſe vpon this laſt Article, they vvere preſently araigned before Iudge Glanduil, vvho contrarie to the vſual cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, vvould needs handle this matter before al others, in the general ſeſſions, which chanced to be there the ſame vveke. An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictement therfore vvas framed, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquly read, charging them that they vvere Seminarie Prieſts; and therfore traitors; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed vvith malice againſt their Quene, and Countrie; vvith other horrible, odious,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:46"/> and wicked termes, moſt fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and iniurious. And then hauing no other proofe, nor vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to produce, the ſame Iudge proteſted to the Iurie, that he vvas aſſured that they were Prieſts; and therfore with manie sharpe words admonished them ſo to find it. The poore Iurie making much difficultie to auerre ſo much, vvithout either confeſſion of the parties, or anie lavvful vvitneſſes againſt them, yet for verie feare, vpon the Iudge his conſcience, againſt their owne conſciences, brought in for their verdict, that the ſaid pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners were guiltie. By and by M. Glanduil gaue ſentence of death againſt them, that <hi>they should returne firſt to the priſon whence they came, thence be drawne on a hurdle to the place of execution, there be hanged til they were halfe dead, then be diſmembred, vnbowled, quartered, and their heads and quarters diſpoſed of, at the the Queens pleaſure.</hi> Which they ioyfully heard, thanked God, and pardoned their perſecutors. But before, and partly alſo after this ſentence, they had diſputation vvith certaine abſurde preachers, that auouched diuerſe ſtrange doctrines, too abominable to be here reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Which neuertheleſſe the glourious Martyrs clerly confuting, ſo confounded the ſame heretiques, and edified the people, that the Magiſtrats commanded the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to hold their peace. And in ſteed of their babling, proſecuted their ovvne farre
<pb facs="tcp:150527:46"/> ſtronger arguments, of fetters, halters, and butchers kniues. Al which the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyrs anſwering vvith true chriſtian courage, receiued their triumphant crou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and put al their perſecutors to that <hi>non plus,</hi> which our bleſſed Sauiour ſpeaketh of: <hi>when they haue killed the bodie, they can do</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And not manie dayes after M. Gla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duil their Iudge, receiued alſo his owne Iudgement, and due pay for his workes. For riding abroad for his pleaſure, nere to his ovvne houſe with one man, ſodainly in the plaine filde, he fel from his horſe to the grounde, the horſe not ſtumbling at al, but running a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay a greate pace, the ſeruant ſtept quickly to his maſter, and aſſaying to help him vp, fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d him dead, wherat being much aſtonished, he poſted ſo faſt as he could to the next villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, crying that his maſter was dead. The people in haſt running to the place found it ſo. And not knowing who elſe could be charged thervvith, they preſently apprehended the ſame ſervingman, vpon ſuſpition that he had murthered his maſter. But vewing the corps, they ſaw euidently, that a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and no man had donne this act. For they found part of his braines ſtraingely comming forth, both at his noſe and mouth, not hauing anie other hurt in his head, but towards the right ſide behind a great dimple
<pb facs="tcp:150527:47"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, vvhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aue pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fiſt; neither his skinne, nor his hat broken at al, nor a heare of his head vvanting to anie mans iudgement. They found likevviſe his right shoulder ſore ſcorched, like burnd leather, as blacke as pitch; and from thence along vpon his arme a great gash, as it had bene made vvith a knife, but not deepe; and in the calfe of his legge on the ſame ſide, they found an other hole, about an inch broad, and three inches deepe, and (which is moſt ſtrange) not ſo much as a threde of his hoſe, nor of his other aparel could bo found to be broken. In the meane while, the horſe that ranne avvay, with much ado vvas ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but could by no meanes be brought nere to the place, vvhere his maſter fel dovvne.</p>
            <p>AGaine the ſame moneth of Iulij, Jan other vertous learned Prieſt, called M. N. Palaſer, by like crueltie was iudged and put to death at Durham; only for that he was a Seminarie Prieſt, and returned to his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, contrarie to the ſtatute made in the 27. yeare of the Quenes raigne. And other three Gentlemen and a gentlewoman vvere alſo condemned to dye, by the ſame ſtatute, for conuerſing vvith the ſame Prieſt, and not bewraying him to the Magiſtrat. Tvvo of the Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, called M. Iohn Norton, and M. N. Talbot receiued their reward, and glorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oune vvith their goſtlie father. Miſtreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:150527:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> Norton (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) being ſuppoſed to be vvithchild was repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The third Gentleman, conſenting of frailtie, to goe to their Church, yet liueth. as the others might haue donne, if they had alſo yelded therunto.</p>
            <p>LIkewiſe at Lancaſter vvithin the ſame moneth, other tvvo Seminarie Prieſts, M. Robert Nutter, and M. Edvvard Thvving vvere condemned and put to death, for their Prieſthood. The elder of them M. Nutter, vvas one of thoſe Prieſts and priſoners, which being brought by their kepers from their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral priſons, to the tovvre wharfe, in the yeare of our Lord, 1585. and there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to enter into a shippe, readie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided to carie them into banishment, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red publikly to the commiſſioners, that they did not accept of that banishment, as of anie grace or mercie at al, for they had not committed anie fault, neither againſt their Quene nor countrie, as this pretended mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie falſly preſuppoſed; and therfore in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe termes requeſted rather to be tried, and to anſvvere their accuſers at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and at Tiburne, then to be thus caried againſt their vvills, out of their natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, from their freinds, and neighboures vvhom they vvere to ſerue, according to their Prieſtlie functions. Affirming moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that though perforce they vvere caried avvay, yet they vvould aſſuredly returne
<pb facs="tcp:150527:48"/> to the ſame worke, ſo ſoone as God, and their ſpiritual Superiors, would permit them ſo to doe. As this bleſſed Martyr for his part, and diuerſe others haue wel and moſt happely performed. M. Thwing was no leſſe reſolued in this glorious quarel, as wel appeared both by his life and death, and particularly by his godlie letters, to his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſiſter, and others, which may be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished in a larger relation. Only here for a taſte of his ſwete and zealous good ſpirit, I shal recite part of two letters written by him in priſon, vnto me that write this. In the former of which, he congratulateth with his friends, his owne impriſonment, in theſe words: <q>My ſelfe am now priſoner for Chriſt, in Lancaſter Caſtle, expecting nothing but execution, at the next Aſſiſes. I deſire you to commend me to the deuout praiers of my freinds with you, that by their help, I may conſummat my courſe to Gods glorie, and the good of my countrie. I pray God proſper you, and al yours, for euer. From my priſon and paradiſe. This laſt of Maij. 1600. <hi>Al yours in Chriſt. E. Th.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>His other letter written but few daies before his martyrdom with like conſolation of his expected good end, he concludeth thus: <q>This day the Iudges come to Lancaſter, where I am in expectation of a happie death, if it ſo pleaſe God almightie. I pray you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me moſt derely to myn vncle, and my
<pb facs="tcp:150527:48"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rother. I pray God bleſſe them both. and to al your good Prieſts and ſcholars, vvhoſe good endeuors God alvvayes proſper, to his owne more glorie. <hi>Ego autem iam delibor, &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus reſolutionis meae inſtat.</hi> before this come vnto you, I shal, if God make me vvorthie, conclude an vnhappie life, with a moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie death. <hi>Omnia poſſum in eo qui me confortat.</hi> From Lancaſter Caſtle, the 21. of Iulij, this holie yeare 1600.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Al yours in Chriſt. EDVVARD THVVEING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>SIX OTHER MARTYRS</head>
            <p>AGaine this laſt ſpring (before the ſame yeare was ended, by our English ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) it hath pleaſed God, to glorifie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more Martyrs in our countrie. VVhoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes I haue alſo thought neceſſarie to adde hereunto, hoping herafter to make more ample relation of them and the reſt. The firſt of theſe vvas M. Iohn Pibush. VVho being condemned about ſix yeares before, only for that he vvas a Seminarie Prieſt; and al that time moſt cruelly vſed, at laſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his happie crovvne, at London the eleuenth of Februarie. And the 27. of the
<pb facs="tcp:150527:49"/> ſame moneth, M. Roger Filcock, and M. Marck Barckvvorth, alſo Seminarie Prieſts, in the ſame place, and for the ſame cauſe, and maiſtris Line a vvidovv gentlewoman, for receiuing priſts in her houſe, receiued the like revvard in erernal glorie.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time alſo, other tvvo Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Prieſts, M. Thurſtan Hunt, and M. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Midleton, being taken in Lancashire, and from thence ſent to London, vvere preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returned thither againe, and ſo condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and executed at Lancaſter meerly for their Prieſthood.</p>
            <p>Thus we haue ſixtene glorious and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Martyrs (beſides thoſe that are ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in priſons, and by other afflictions, for the ſame faith) vvithin the ſpace of twelue moneths, that is, in this one holie yeare, for euerie hundreth yeare ſince Chriſt one. A moſt happie Iubiley to them; a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r conſolation to al Catholiques; and a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie example alſo of Gods mercie, tovvards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of other Religions, that vvil conſider their ovvne eſtates, vvherin they liue; and the true cauſe, for which al theſe, and ſome hundreths more theſe late yeares, haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovved their liues. For ſo they shal clerly ſee, that they vvere al accuſed and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, for the old, true Holie, Catholique, and Apoſtolique faith; as offenders againſt certaine nevv Statutes made of late (the like neuer heard of before in a Chriſtian Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
<pb facs="tcp:150527:49"/> nor as yet approued for good, elsvvhere in the vvorld) and moſt ſpecially vrged to go to the Proteſtants Churches. Which alone would haue ſaued their temporal liues longer.</p>
            <p>For the ſame cauſe alſo manie other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and moſt conſtant Catholique pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners in the Citie of Yorke, by the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the L. Burley, Preſident of the North partes, and his aſſiſtants, haue bene this yeare violently, and often dravvne and haled, by meere force to heretical Sermons. And aftervvards, becauſe they reproued the prechers for diuerſe blasphemies, and other falſe and abſurde doctrines, haue bene shut vp in ſtreicter priſons, laden with irons, and pinched vvith famine; neither did they forbeare, nor feare, to reprehend blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, vvhen they vvere brought to the ſame place againe. But certaine of them bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g learned, openly reproued the blaſphemous prechers, and aftervvards before the ſame Preſident, and others, clerly confuted their errors. Others of leſſe learning, yet alſo of great zeale, ſtopped their ovvne eares, in fight of the perſecutors. who therfore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ech of them, two men to hold downe their hands, al the ſermon time. and yet would they not for al that, harken to the ſermons, but partly by ſtrugling and chiding with their tormenters, partly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whiſpering and talking among themſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150527:50"/> they made ſuch a blacke <hi>Sanctus,</hi> that neit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> one nor other could much marke, vvhat the preacher ſaid. So vnpoſſible it is, either for Catholiques to be inreſt, or for perſecuters to haue their vvole vvilles, vvhere the furie of hereſie rageth. And much leſſe is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to extinguish the Catholique faith by force and violence. for the more it is ſovved with teares, and watered vvith bloud, the more it increaſeth and proſpereth, As we ſee not only in the primitue Church, but alſo novv in England, where through Gods ſpecial grace, and by the prayers and bloud of ſo manie Martyrs, there be farre more Catholiques at this day, then were fourtie yeares agoe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>DEO GRATIAS. Yours al and euer: T. W. a Seminarie Priest.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:50"/>
            <head>AN ADVERTISMENT TO THE READER, touching the contents, order, and title of this booke.</head>
            <p>INtending at firſt (gentle reader) to make a briefe relation of tenne Martyrs, in the holie yeare; and by the maner of proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt them, to declare that they ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red meerly for Religion; I put M. Iohn Rigbie his proceſſe firſt (though he was not the firſt of theſe Martyrs) becauſe I ment to ſet the ſame downe more at large, as being moſt notorious, and moſt amply hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in publique place of Iuſtice. But when I had donne ſo much, and (by reaſon of a iorney that I made) leift it with a freind to publish, for the common good; vpon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine conſiderations, it was not pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed as I expected. And in the meane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that it was opprobriouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to M. Wharton (as alſo to ſome others, to the offence of manie, and ſcandal of the weake) that the Seminarie Prieſts were at diſſention, and debate againſt Ieſuites, I thought good, to explicat more fully his anſwer, to that falſe and abſurde ſclander. And hearing alſo, that it hath pleaſed God, to glorifie ſix more Martyrs, I would in nowiſe omit to adde their names herunto. By which occaſions I vvas forced alſo to change the former title, to make it confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the whole contents.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. W.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:51"/>
            <p>Hunc libellum, cui titulus eſt, Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio de ſexdecim martyribus &amp;c. cum declaratione quòd Catholici Angli perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutionem ſuſtineant pro fide orthodoxa; &amp; quòd inter Seminariſtas ſacerdotes Anglos ac Patres Societ. Ieſu benè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniat; à viris Anglicae linguae peritis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; eruditionis Theologicae nomine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perlectum, nec quicquam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſum habere quod editionem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediat; excudi permiſimus. Actum Duaci, menſe Septembri. 1601.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Bartholomaeus Petrus, S. Th. Doct. &amp; Profeſſ.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:150527:51"/>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> dubios <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tus aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uo falſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> depoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more ſequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> locus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
